<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Fifteen comforts of rash and inconsiderate marriage, or, Select animadversions upon the miscarriages of a wedded state done out of French.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 181 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 74 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41291</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F886</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40891</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19526849</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19526849</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109001</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41291)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109001)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1686:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Fifteen comforts of rash and inconsiderate marriage, or, Select animadversions upon the miscarriages of a wedded state done out of French.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The fourth edition</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[16], 128 [i.e. 126], [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Crooke, and Matth. Gillyflower,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Error in paging: p. 57 and 58 skipped in the numbering.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]-[2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriage --  Anecdotes</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109001:1"/>
            <p>The Fifteen COMFORTS OF <hi>Raſh and Inconſiderate</hi> MARRIAGE. OR, Select Animadverſions UPON THE <hi>MISCARRIAGES</hi> OF A <hi>WEDDED STATE.</hi> Done out of <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Fourth Edition, with the Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of three Comforts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Crooke,</hi> and <hi>Matth. Gillyflower,</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:109001:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109001:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>IT is an Old Saying, That every thing grows worſe and worſe, which the <hi>Venu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> Poet ſeems to confirm in theſe following words, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch to the ſame purpoſe,
<q>
                  <l>Aetas Parentum, pejor Avis, tulit</l>
                  <l>Nos Nequiores, mox daturos</l>
                  <l>Progeniem Vitioſiorem.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding whoſe Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ty, and the pretended Antiquity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ereof, I'll be bold to affirm, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Adage in the Vulgar and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ken Application thereof, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s neither Sence nor Reaſon with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> having no other Baſis to ſupport
<pb facs="tcp:109001:3"/> it, but Malice, Ignorance, or both; and tho' this Treatiſe ſhould not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely prove the contrary, it will at leaſt ſhake, if not totally explode<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that common Opinion, <hi>viz.</hi> That Woman is the worſt piece of the Hexameron Creation, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, according to the <hi>Maſculine</hi> tho' in truth, meerly Sophiſtica Logick of this Modern Age, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come (the more the pity) the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of all the Raillery, or (in down right Engliſh) Railing againſt tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> harmleſs and innocent Sex; and queſtion not but by this Diſcourſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all Diſſenters will be of my Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that if ever Vertue did appea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſhine with Glory, Splendo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and its own Native and Charmin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Beauty in any created Subſtanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it is moſt viſible and conſtant in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Female, I muſt ingenuouſly confe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> that I have a particular Inclinatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to, and Deference for that Sex, hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ing my ſelf obliged to vindica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:109001:3"/> them from thoſe Calumnies where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they have been ſo foulely and cauſleſly aſperſed by Ancient, as well as Modern Authors; nor am I to blame for deſerting my own Cauſe, to juſtifie what may ſeem againſt my ſelf, and eſpouſe the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitable Condition and defence of the contrary, and ſo much injur'd Party. This is the Compoſition of ſome Amorous Perſon, who anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the ſame Spirit and Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction as I am, hath undertaken (and judged it his Duty too) to ſatisfie you, and (he hopes) ſo far as to work upon you a Perſuaſion that the Modeſty, Baſhfulneſs, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onaireté, and Civility, together with all Qualifications that adorn and beautifie the Soul, are as Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplarily eminent in Women of this Age, as ever they were in any of the former; and inſtruct you to ſet a value on their Actions, as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt Creatures in the worſt of
<pb facs="tcp:109001:4"/> Times, whoſe Vertue muſt need ſhine with the greater Luſtre, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubject to the vain Aſſault<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Ineffectual Temptations o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Men, grown old (like the Times in Wickedneſs, Malice and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge.</p>
            <trailer>Farewe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:109001:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE Philoſophers and Sages of former Times, as well as thoſe of a later Date, have ſpent <hi>Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram &amp; Oleum,</hi> exhauſted their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pirits, and waſted their Bodies, till at laſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their Indefatigable Pains and Induſtry, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ey crumbled into duſt, and all to incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate this Doctrine, grounded upon ſolid Reaſon; that it is certainly a greater Happineſs for a Man to enjoy Freedom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncontroul'd, than to enſlave himſelf for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver without Compulſion. He muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſity forfeit his Reaſon, that is of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ary Opinion; for as a Modern Poet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ings truly;
<q>
                  <l>Surely their Heads unpeopled are with Brains,</l>
                  <l>That hug their Fetters, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace their Chains.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>That man is unqueſtionably ſenceleſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho enjoys his Freedom in the Vigor and Sprightlineſs of his youth, living in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ream of wealth and the high Tide of Pleaſure and Delight, is careſs'd by For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,
<pb facs="tcp:109001:5"/> laden with Favours, and almoſt cloy'd with Comforts; a Perſon that may cry <hi>Sciolto</hi> to his Paſſions, give them the looſe Rein, gratifie his Appetite and Guſt, with whatſoever three of the four Elements can furniſh him; and yet this Perſon, notwithſtanding all theſe Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, throws himſelf into an Abyſs of miſery, confines himſelf to a Perſon (a Wife) whoſe beſt Qualification is Pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhneſs, forfeits his Freedom, Reaſon, Content, and Satisfaction, and loſeth his own, to enſlave himſelf to the Humour of another; and this too for Life, for whom the Art and Wit of the Pregnant and Subtile can never procure a Ranſom in order to Redemption. Would not any rational Creature judge him guilty of Statute-madneſs, who being ſhewn the Loathſomneſs and Horror of a Dungeon, views the maigre and ghoſt-like Aſpect of the famiſhed Priſoner, hears the hideous Shrieks and Groans of ſhackled Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors, the ratling noiſe of whoſe heavy Irons is a Harmony only fit to drive a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Man out of his Wits; would not, I ſay, any Perſon gifted with Reaſon, look upon him to be mad beyond the Cure of Drugs or Medicines, who ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs ſhake hands with his Liberty,
<pb facs="tcp:109001:5"/> and the unaccountable delights that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it, and caſt himſelf into a Goal, with a reſolution never to be diſcharged, but to lie there and periſh? The very Brutes, tho' never ſo ſtupid, or wild, value their Roaming Liberty at the higheſt Rate: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarding, nay, loſing their Life, which is their All, their whole Being, their little E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity (pardon the Expreſſion,) to preſerve their Freedom; and ſhall Man, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Creation, endow'd with a rational Soul, inſpir'd by the Deity, come ſhort of Inanimate Power. Inconſiderable Animals, in a buſineſs of ſuch weight and concernment, upon which the Contentation, and in truth, Felicity of Human Life doth conſiſt? <hi>Dii avertant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider farther to confirm this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Deſire and Love of Freedom and Liberty, is ſo innate in all Perſons, that not only Man, but Woman, the weaker Sex, nay, Children, a weaker part of the weaker Sex, have hazarded, nay, loſt Wealth, Fortune, and Life, rather than part with ſo precious a Jewel. The ſad Cataſtrophes of Perſons and Kingdoms, the horrid Maſſacres and Murders, the Torments, Plagues, Battels, Quarrels and Diſcontents between Nations and Parties, the Depopulation of Republicks, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhing
<pb facs="tcp:109001:6"/> of Kingdoms, the Extirpating of Princes, the Aſſaſſinating Kings, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors (a Curſe on the Diſciples of Lame <hi>Loyola</hi> for that King-killing Tenet) nay, moſt of the Barbarous Tragedies that have been acted upon the bloody Stage of this World, have had no other ſource than the natural Deſire and Affection of Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (how juſtly I diſpute not) and Property, the Darling Twins of Mankind, ever ſince the firſt Prevarication.</p>
            <p>The wild Beaſts of the deſart are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnar'd and taken in Pit-falls by the Craft and Cunning of the wary Huntſman, who with Artifice contrives them ſo, that they are narrow at Top, and broad at the Bottom, from whence there is no poſſibility of Eſcape, but they muſt continue a Prey to the over-wily Man that made the Sn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, and ſo the Brute loſeth the Liberty which kind Nature conferr'd upon him, and unkind Man Craftily deprives him of. The ſame thing may he ſaid of thoſe that are married, when they are once enchained and fettered with the Bands of Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, a ſad ſtate (as it often falls out, if they once fall into it) from whence there is no Redemption. The ſilly, mute fiſh, after the ſame manner, labors with divers turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to wind it ſelf into the Net, Baited
<pb facs="tcp:109001:6"/> thereunto, till at laſt ſhe loſeth her Life and Liberty. This Net in truth is the Net of Matrimony, and the Youthful Precipitate, Heedleſs Hot-ſpurs of this Age, whoſe Chins are ſearce cover'd with ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Down, are the Fiſhes without the Net, who fancy to themſelves, that they may Bathe and Swim in a Calm and undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd ſtream of Pleaſure, and at laſt launch out into a Torrent, or rather Sea of miſery, encompaſſed with nothing but Storms and Tempeſts to their contimial di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance and vexation, having loſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in an incloſure, that they can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther break through, nor leap over, but there live diſcontentedly, languiſh painfully, till they dwindle away to nothing, and ſo at laſt Die miſerable. It is a ſaying of the Learned <hi>Scaliger,</hi> that a Wife is an Hectic Fever, never to be cur'd by any thing hut Death, nor can any wiſe Man deny it.</p>
            <p>The report is current of a famous Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, <hi>Valere</hi> by Name, who being ask'd by one of his Friends, (that had the misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to be catch'd in the Nooze of Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock,) whether he had done well in chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his condition of ſingle Life, returned him this bitter, tho' true Anſwer; Friend (ſaid he) could you not find out ſome Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipice
<pb facs="tcp:109001:7"/> to caſt your ſelf headlong from thence into the Sea? intimating thereby, that be had made a better Election, had he gain'd ſome high Rock, and precipitated himſelf into the Fathomleſs Ocean, there to conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate at once all his Miſeries, rather than involve himſelf in a Turbulent Sea, the diſtractions, diſcontents and Vexations of a Wedded State, never to be redreſſed; a Malady that bids defiance to the power of any Drug or Doctor, how famous or exquiſite ſoever.</p>
            <p>Great and inexpreſſible was the Regret and ſorrow of the Arch-deacon of <hi>Tours</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> who being ſo infatuated (ſhall I ſay) or faſcinated, as to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Happy, and Religious Life of a Clerk, with all its appendent Priviledges, married the Reverſion of another, (a Widdow) and fooliſhly fell into a Quag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, wherein one had been drown'd before him; with whom being link'd by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſoluble and Gordian-Knot of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, he led a tedious life, or to ſpeak more properly, endur'd a Vaſſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ge almoſt inſupportable; for which be ſang a mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Ditty, to the Tune of — <gap reason="blank: omitted in print" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Fortune my Foe,</hi> why haſt thou married me, and chaunted a Cordial Palinode, reſerving to himſelf only this
<pb facs="tcp:109001:7"/> Comfort, that he had ſome hope by his own Miſcarriage, to forwarn others from the like Inadvertency and Raſhneſs, and to that purpoſe compos'd ſeveral Learned Treatiſes, to dehort all Men from ſuch unadviſed Enterprizes and Attempts. Nor is he ſingular herein; for many perſons of great Parts, and known Abilities, have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to diſcover the Servitude, and more than <hi>Egyptian</hi> Bondage of a Coup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Condition; and in my Judgment, to be Free without Cenſoriouſneſs, the Eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Comforts of Matrimony herein fully diſplay'd, and clearly laid open, are the greateſt Misfortunes, Pains, Diſcontents, and Torments that can enter into the Thoughts of Man. Yet for all that is premention'd, I do not blame the State of Matrimony (as now inſtituted by the Church) for beyond all diſpute, Marriage is an Eccleſiaſtical and Religious Tye, a Boundary to Extravagancy, giving a Check to the exorbitant paſſions of the wild and hot-headed Youth of both Sexes, and confining them to one perſon, which is but Juſt and Lawful, and not permit them, like brutes to range about in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, or the Sect of <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> who differ'd little from Beaſts in that Prophane and Diſſolute Tenet of theirs, Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb facs="tcp:109001:8"/> of Women; nor do I find fault with thoſe that marry; I am of their Opinion, and ſay they do well; for we ſojourn in this World to endure and ſuffer Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to allay the heighth of our Pride, and give a Check to all Eccentrick and Irregular Paſſions, that after the miſeries of this Life, we may thereby be prepar'd and fitted for a happy and bleſſed Eſtate hereafter. And indeed I do not think that a Man can by the Compaſs of this Life ſail into a deeper Ocean of Miſery and Affliction, conſidering the inevitable Grievouſneſs and indiſpenſible continuance of a Married Life (I mean only ſuch as raſhly and unadviſedly without due conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the Temper and Conſtitution of one another meet and marry, the want of which good Election and Choice ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Wedded ſtate ſo Burthenſome and inſupportable) which undoubtedly exceeds all the Racks and Engines of Torment that the Barbarity of Tyrants, and the malitious Wit ef Man ever invented; but yet when a Husband is once inur'd and accuſtomed to the Domeſtic Jars of a double Life, and like the Aſs, bears the burthen patiently, which cuſtom hath made ſo Tolerable, that he prides himſelf in his fondneſs, patience, and long ſuffeirng; of
<pb facs="tcp:109001:8"/> this, in fine, there may be made a good Application, or at leaſt be may make a vertue of neceſſity: for that is but a Foppiſh and vain Conceit of ſome empty Pates, that Patience <hi>per</hi> force is a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine for a mad Dog, and ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y not worth the refutation. To conclude, I have taken ſome Pains in compoſing theſe Fifteen Comforts of Matrimony, for the ſatisfaction of thoſe who are in that State; and I am confident dare not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict them, without they give their Wives the Lye, when they are once faſt and intangled in the Net; and for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of others, by way of Caution, from running the ſame Riſque, the utmoſt Remedy whereof is a thread-bare Patience, or a whining Recantation; or if they muſt venture upon this Charybdis, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void Ship-wrack in ſo dangerous a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, let them look before they leap, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the old Proverb, and elect ſuch a Perſon as may be link'd in Temper and Humor, whoſe Souls may he united as well as their Bodies, that ſo their Hour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſs may run to the laſt Sand without Interruption or Moleſtation, and they have a Numerous happy Iſſue, (the dear Pledges of a Married Life) to perpetuate their Name and Memory, that their
<pb facs="tcp:109001:9"/> Aſhes may leave a fragrant ſmell to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity; for otherwiſe if they embrace this Holy Ordinance, without due and ſerious Conſideration, (upon which moment depends their Happineſs upon Earth) they deſerve the Burial of an Aſs, and by my conſent ſhall drop into the Grave without either Tears or Pity.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109001:9"/>
            <div n="1" type="comment">
               <head>THE Firſt COMFORT. Young Formality, and a Foppiſh Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Citt.</head>
               <p>YOUTH is naturally inclined to Mirth and Gallantry, with all the Briskneſs and Gaiety ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable; has Limbs agile and active, fancying nothing but Muſick, Dancing, Balls and Plays, where the Variety of <hi>Female</hi> Objects fire the Young <hi>Sparks,</hi> in ſo much as <hi>Love</hi> ſoon breaks out, and many times to their Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and Deſtruction. In this <hi>Heat</hi> of Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion the <hi>Youngster</hi> viſits Ladies, Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments after the new mode, Careſſes them with all demonſtrations of <hi>fervent Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,</hi> makes his <hi>Amours</hi> with a kind of ſtarch'd Formality, which turns all into Ridicule, tho poſſibly that ſet way of Courſhip may pleaſe the Foppiſh Female <hi>Cit,</hi> and gratifie her Childiſh Humour: Thus far he proceeds with Applauſe and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:109001:10"/> Acceptance, but this will no way ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Young Gentleman, he muſt come to <hi>Embraces,</hi> free her from the Curſe of Barrenneſs, and himſelf from the Scandal of Impotence; and now the Game be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins; he is pregnant with <hi>Love</hi> and muſt be delivered, tho the Remedy proves ten times worſe than the Diſeaſe; in ſhort he plies the buſineſs ſo <hi>briskly,</hi> and purſues her with that Warmth and Conſtancy, that ſhe can no longer reſiſt, but in ſpight of all her <hi>Maiden Modeſty,</hi> muſt yield to his Propoſals, tho ſhe perchance Counterfeit a <hi>Bluſh</hi> at the Condeſcention, ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as ready to comply with <hi>him,</hi> as he to apply himſelf to <hi>her,</hi> and as willing to underſtand the Sweets of the Marriage Bed, as the Hot Youth that ſo vigorouſly purſues her. Thus in a ſhort time the whole Buſineſs is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, and the Solemnity of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony perform'd with as much, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more Vanity and Expence than is conſiſtent with the Ability of either, or both of them; but fall back, fall edge, the <hi>Knot</hi> is tied, never to be looſened, but by Death, the <hi>Prieſt</hi> having joyn'd them ſo firmly together, that 'tis impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to un-hand them again; tho pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably before the Moon hath run her
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109001:10"/> Menſtruous Courſe, the <hi>Husband</hi> may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear like that Grand Luminary in her firſt Quarter, and ſhe curſe the Canonical Garb that faſtned them in ſo ſtrict a Band as that of Marriage, as will appear, and that very ſuddenly.</p>
               <p>Now you muſt imagine, that our <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant</hi> minds nothing for the preſent, but the ſatiating himſelf with Delight, Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings, Treats, and ſuch kind of Diverſions as uſually attend ſuch ridiculous and idle Conjunctions. There appears as yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Mirth</hi> and <hi>Jollity,</hi> no Scene of Sorrow is admitted in this Comedy; his whole deſign is to pleave and court his Wife with raviſhing Addreſſes, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands nothing but what ſhe approves, nor entertains his Thoughts with any thing but the Contrivance of preſenting her with <hi>Bagatels</hi> and little <hi>Toys,</hi> ſuch as are apt to gratifie the vain Humor of a foppiſh young <hi>Girl,</hi> drawn into the Net, and wheadled or cajol'd into the Pit of <hi>Marriage:</hi> well, no matter, let them both run their own Career; theſe ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Bleſſings, this Counterfet Felicity, this mask'd Love, and vizarded Content, will prove but ſhort-liv'd, and then let the troubles of the whole time after be balanced with thoſe few ſuppoſitious and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109001:11"/> imaginary Delights they enjoyed in the Infancy of their <hi>Marriage,</hi> and the Vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the one will out-weigh the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the other, by ſo many degrees, that Arithmetick it ſelf can never deſcribe its true and due Proportion. Now the time of Dalliance being over, and the Cares of the World coming upon them, you ſhall underſtand a ſtrange and unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Alteration, which we may call, (and I hope without Offence) the Firſt <hi>Comfort</hi> of <hi>Matrimony.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the <hi>Wife</hi> we muſt ſuppoſe to be well acquainted with the cunning In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues of a <hi>married Woman,</hi> and is not to be taught her Leſſon; Feaſts, Goſſip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Treats, have inſtructed her ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently how to perſonate the <hi>ſubtile Wife</hi> with an <hi>Uxorious Husband,</hi> and ſhe begins to make an eſſay of her <hi>Woman-Craft</hi> according to the humor of thoſe ſhe converſed with in the Female Cabals, uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally frequented by her; and thus ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to play her <hi>Pranks:</hi> The other day ſhe was invited to a Regale, a very noble Treat indeed, where there was nothing wanting to gratifie the Appetite; ſhe took great notice of the Habit and Attire of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Wives</hi> of her own Rank and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, how richly they were accoutred, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109001:11"/> after the neweſt Mode; this was ſo great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Eye-ſore to her, that ſhe watched an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ortunity to diſcloſe her mind to her <hi>Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>band,</hi> thinking it but reaſonable that ſhe ſhould appear as gay and as Genteel as the <hi>beſt Dame</hi> in the Pariſh. Now you muſt obſerve by the way, that that Woman, who is once intoxicated with the <hi>Cup</hi> of <hi>Matrimony,</hi> is very ſtrangely qualified, and differently tempered from moſt of her Sex, if ſhe be not once in twenty four hours troubled with the <hi>Sullens</hi> or the <hi>Pouts</hi> (a Diſeaſe as natural to her as Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiping, and both incurable) tho counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit and cauſleſs; and where think you is the Scene of her Sullenneſs? why, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly <hi>in Bed,</hi> a place where Womens feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Tears and Sighs have an excellent Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of <hi>perſwaſion;</hi> and now being brought to Bed, let us examine her De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment, there ſhe lies like the Statue of <hi>Niobe</hi> petrified, and for a time as ſenceleſs; whereupon the <hi>amorous Husband</hi> begins to accoſt her with Accollado's and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces, asking her what is the matter, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thee, my Dear, (ſaith he) for he can for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear no longer, what ail'ſt thou? To whom ſhe ſnappiſhly replies, <hi>let me alone, don't diſturb me,</hi> I am very much indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and have reaſon enough too, God
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109001:12"/> knows, but you never regard what I ſay, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> or ſuffer, your <hi>Unkindneſs</hi> ſticks ſo cloſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to my heart, that nothing will remove it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but Death; I'm ſure I ſhall never reſt, but in that place of undiſturbed Reſt (the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Dormitory of Mortals) the Grave. <hi>Deareſt!</hi> ſaith he, you pierce my very Heart, and wound me to the Soul with ſuch ſevere Language: Why, If I ſhould acquaint you with my Diſturbance, it were to no purpoſe; for I'm confident you would ſlight it, or which is as bad, think I have private <hi>ſelf-ends</hi> or <hi>deſigns</hi> in it: No, no, you ſhall tell me, I am reſolv'd, come what will on't: Well Sir, ſince you impoſe your Commands upon me, I will obey. You are not inſenſible, I'm ſure, that not long ſince I was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited to a Collation, tho I had not gone, but with your <hi>permiſſion</hi> and <hi>approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> yet when I was there, with great grief I ſpeak it, I heartily wiſht my ſelf at home agen; for there was not one <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual</hi> Woman in the whole Company, tho of the meaneſt Rank, but was more <hi>gayly cloath'd</hi> than my ſelf; I do not ſpeak it out of Pride, tho, I think, I may ſay without Oſtentation, that I am as well <hi>extracted,</hi> have had as <hi>good Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> have as <hi>commendable</hi> a Face,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109001:12"/> Carriage and Complexion, without the <hi>Artificial Embeliſhments</hi> of Paint, Patch and Powder, as the proudeſt ſhe of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll. As to my own particular, I ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y proteſt, upon the Faith of an honeſt Woman, I do not value the outward Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aments of Aparrel: For the gaudieſt Robes are but the Badges of our <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Shame:</hi> It is only for your Credit, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Reputation of our Friends and Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions that I am ſo much concern'd. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hee how <hi>gloriouſly</hi> did they appear? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome in Flower'd <hi>Sattin Gowns,</hi> embroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ered with Gold; Petticoats adorn'd with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he beſt <hi>Point de Veniſe,</hi> attir'd with their Hair, and their ears adorn'd with <hi>coſtly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>endants,</hi> their Necks encompaſſed with Pearls, and the graver ſort in the beſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hree-Pil'd Velvet; inſomuch that I, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>earing only in my <hi>wedding Gown,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat, tho nigh worn out, the <hi>beſt Suit</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> my Ward-robe, could not forbear bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng all the time I was in Company; nay, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>at which troubled me moſt, was, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne or two of our Neighbours told me, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ey did admire my Husband was not <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>amed</hi> to ſee me go in ſo <hi>mean a Garb.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o which the good man replies, Sweet Heart, you know, that we have been at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reat Charges to furniſh our ſelves ſo well
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109001:13"/> as we are; that <hi>Trading</hi> decays, Loſſes have befallen us: I have a chargeable <hi>Suit at Law</hi> to defend next Term for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of <hi>your Portion,</hi> which will coſt me many a fair Pound before I enjoy it. Ay, ay, (quoth ſhe) I did Imagine as much, and expect no other from you, but (what I am now ſenſible to my Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row) Reproaches; and ſo in a Pet ſhe flings out of his <hi>Arms</hi> with <hi>Scorn</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation;</hi> pray let me alone, don't come near me; and I'll aſſure you for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I'll never <hi>open my Lips</hi> to you agen as long as I breath upon this acount; therefore pray reſt ſatisfied: But hold, Love, are you angry without a cauſe? No, no, the contrary is too apparent; the <hi>Portion ſticks in my ſtomach</hi> as well as yours; had you had nothing with me I am not in a Capacity to beſtow any thing upon you now, my Love and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to you, methinks ſhould prevent ſuch <hi>Reflections;</hi> but you know, as mean as I was, that I was <hi>Courted</hi> by ſeveral before ever you made any Addreſs to me, who would have been glad with all their hearts to have <hi>married</hi> me without ſo much as a Smock to cover my Shame, had not you interpos'd and gained my Heart, which now you ſtudy to plague
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109001:13"/> and Torment. O unfortunate Woman <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat I am! but I muſt be <hi>content</hi> with my <hi>choice,</hi> and <hi>bear</hi> all as patiently as I can; would I were as deep in the ground as I am high, and then you would be rid of me, and I of my trouble: Really Love, ſaith the Novice, you do not well in uſing of me thus, <hi>ask what you pleaſe,</hi> and you ſhall have it to the utmoſt of my Ability; but yet I muſt have a Care of the main Chance; prithee turn to me, my dear: for Gods ſake, let me be <hi>quiet;</hi> if you thought no more of <hi>fondneſs</hi> in this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, than I do, you would never come near me more, I am not ſo Buckſom, I'll aſſure you: Ay, but Child, ſaith he, in a <hi>Jocular</hi> way, if my Head were once laid, you would ſoon be <hi>Married</hi> agen, I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant you; would I, (ſaith ſhe) in truth, I find ſo little <hi>Pleaſure</hi> or <hi>Comfort</hi> in a Wedded Condition, that if I were once <hi>unmarried,</hi> I would be ſo far from it, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he beſt he, that ever laid Leg over Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſhould never ſo much as <hi>touch</hi> my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ips, as long as I have a day to live, take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat from me, and be ſatisfied. With <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his kind of <hi>Diſſimulation</hi> ſhe entertains <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Fop, who is both in Pleaſure and Pain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t once; in Pleaſure to think ſhe is ſo <hi>Cold</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd <hi>Chaſt</hi> a Wife; in Pain, becauſe he
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109001:14"/> ſees her ſo much <hi>diſturbed.</hi> Thus ſhe Treats him all Day with a <hi>Contracted Brow,</hi> and all night with ſuch <hi>flattering Diſcourſes,</hi> not one good word is he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of, ſo that he is forced to <hi>beat</hi> his Brains for Money to <hi>purchaſe</hi> the <hi>Rich</hi> Gown and Petticoat, the want of which is the <hi>Source</hi> and <hi>Original</hi> of both their Diſcontents. Well! they muſt be had, <hi>quo jure, quaque injuria,</hi> by Hook, or by Crook, no <hi>ſlumher</hi> will ſeize upon his Eye lids, till this be procured; away he goes, <hi>ſuſque deque,</hi> hand over head, taking up, upon <hi>Credit,</hi> Silks, Laces, Jewels, and what not, and then returns home in Triumph, with the <hi>Spoil</hi> of the Mercer's Shop, and calls down his <hi>Wife</hi> to ſurvey the <hi>deſired Purchaſe;</hi> which ſhe no ſooner ſpies, but like acunning Baggage diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and ſays, Fy, <hi>Husband,</hi> in troth, you are now to blame, theſe are <hi>too Rich</hi> Veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for a perſon of my Condition, they will not at all become me, I fear: beſhrew the hearts of thoſe <hi>lofty Dames,</hi> that firſt invented ſuch coſtly Apparel; I would not give ſix pence for the <hi>beſt Gown</hi> that ever Female body was Tenant to: but however, ſince you have been ſo kind, let me beg one <hi>ſupernumerary favour of you</hi> not to <hi>hit</hi> me in the Teeth hereafter with
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109001:14"/> it, and ſay, I put you to this chargeable expence: for upon my <hi>Reputation</hi> (and that is not to be valued) it was none of my intention; I deſire no other <hi>Garb</hi> than what is requiſite for <hi>Warmth</hi> and <hi>Decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</hi> Now all is well, and the Man ſhall have his Mare agen; they live lovingly and quietly till the <hi>day</hi> (O that fatal day!) of <hi>Payment;</hi> the Money cannot be procur'd to ſtop the Mouths of his Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, who being diſappointed, uſe the utmoſt <hi>rigour</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> againſt him, ſeize his Body and Goods, extend his Lands, turn his Wife a grazing into the <hi>wide World,</hi> where ſhe has only the liberty of chooſing what Kingdom ſhe pleaſes to <hi>beg</hi> in, and he, poor <hi>undone Man,</hi> is clapt into a Goal, there to endure a cloſe and beggarly Confinement, <hi>durante vita;</hi> where he has <hi>time</hi> and <hi>room enough</hi> to lament his Deplorable Condition. The Woman ſhe returns to her Friends, Curſing the hour that ſhe was born in: never ſuch a diſgrace befel a Woman of her Birth and Education. Alas! Alas! (ſaith ſhe) have I ſtudied <hi>oeconomie</hi> all my life long, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſo much <hi>pains</hi> in <hi>governing</hi> my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, been as <hi>ſparing</hi> as any <hi>good Wife</hi> in the Pariſh, and all to keep both ends together, and is it come to <hi>this</hi> at laſt? O
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109001:15"/> Death, come and put a Period to my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery! Thus the <hi>harmleſs Woman</hi> bemoans her misfortune, lays all the fault at the poor Man's door, (poor Man indeed) and now he is <hi>faſt</hi> in the <hi>Net,</hi> and the more he ſtruggles, the more he is intangled; in ſhort, he's laid up for his Life, and his Creditors, (for that's all they're like to have) may make <hi>Dice</hi> of his <hi>Bones.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="comment">
               <head>The Second COMFORT. The Credulous Coxcomb, the Gadding Jilt, and Couſin-Gallant.</head>
               <p>IT is the Misfortune of <hi>ſome</hi> Men, (and thoſe <hi>ſome</hi> are too many, God wot) to prepoſſeſs themſelves with a Conceit, that Reaſon, Sence and Demonſtration can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver convince them of; ſuch is the caſe of the <hi>Husband</hi> that enjoys the <hi>ſecond Comfort of Matrimony</hi> we are now diſcourſing of, who will not be perſuaded by all the World, but ſhe is the <hi>Hanſomeſt Woman</hi> in it, tho he is much miſtaken; but I cannot blame him; for <hi>Beauty</hi> is nothing but <hi>meer Fancy,</hi> and if I conceit black and blue to be a comely Complexion, it is ſo to me: Having thus in his own Opinion Married a <hi>Fine Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> he maintains her as <hi>finely:</hi> Her
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109001:15"/> brisk humour inclines her to <hi>Viſits, Treats,</hi> and <hi>Jovial Meetings;</hi> tho this her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band diſreliſheth, but all to no purpoſe; for ſhe's of a <hi>gadding</hi> temp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, and out ſhe muſt for Health and Recreation; but how to contrive the way to effect it quietly, <hi>hic labor, hoc opus;</hi> ſhe is invited to a Feaſt, and a <hi>pretended Friend</hi> or Relation (who is no more of kin to her than Sir <hi>George</hi> is to the Dragon) however he comes to her, and ſhe Salutes him by the name of <hi>Couſin,</hi> good <hi>Couſin,</hi> dear <hi>Couſin!</hi> and her Mother, to palliate the buſineſs, calls him ſo too, ſhe knowing the better how to manage that <hi>Amorous Affair,</hi> becauſe it hath been her <hi>own Condition</hi> formerly; but the Husband is unwilling to have her go, alledging many <hi>faint</hi> and <hi>frivolous</hi> Excuſes; yet to take off all <hi>Jealouſie</hi> from the Good-man, her Friend will ſay, in good Faith, Couſin, I have <hi>no mind</hi> at all to go to this <hi>Feaſt,</hi> I have buſineſs to do, nor would I ſet a foot over the Threſhold, God knows my heart, were it not for <hi>your</hi> and my <hi>ſhe Couſins</hi> Credit; and you know 'tis neither Modeſt nor Modiſh, for a Gentlewoman of her Rank to <hi>beſtow Viſits</hi> without an Attendant; tho I am ſatisfied ſhe is <hi>averſe</hi> to any ſuch kind of Promenade, or Collation; for of <hi>all Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:109001:16"/> that ever I knew, when ſhe is <hi>abroad</hi> ſhe makes ſuch ado to <hi>come home,</hi> that ſhe almoſt diſturbs the Company. The ſilly Fop now begins to <hi>encline</hi> and <hi>grant</hi> the Requeſt; but firſt asks <hi>what Company</hi> they expect at this Entertainment? Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Company indeed Couſin! there will be your <hi>Mother-in-Law,</hi> my <hi>Wife,</hi> your <hi>Couſin,</hi> Mr. ſuch a ones <hi>Daughter,</hi> and moſt of the <hi>good Neighbourhood;</hi> Company fit for a Princeſs, Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Quality. Well (quoth the Man) <hi>you may go,</hi> for this once, but I hope you don't intend to make a <hi>Trade on't,</hi> have a care of your ſelf, and be ſure you don't bring Night home with you. <hi>Leave</hi> being thus obtained, the <hi>ſubtle Lady</hi> feigns an unwillingneſs, ſaying, indeed Love! I care not for <hi>going out</hi> at preſent, let me intreat you that I may <hi>ſtay at home;</hi> but he, having a great Confidence in the Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, ſays, nay, nay, ſweet Heart, I would not have you ſo <hi>ungentile,</hi> as to diſappoint your Neighbours, ſince you are ready, and the Aſſignation is <hi>pre-deſign'd,</hi> prethee, Child go; whereupon away ſhe <hi>frisks</hi> like Lightning with her Couſin-Gallant, fleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the way at the <hi>contented one</hi> at home, ſaying, that he has ſome ſmall ſmack of Jealouſie, (and a great deal of Reaſon
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109001:16"/> for it.) To the <hi>Place</hi> they come, and are no ſooner arrived, but ſhe is <hi>Nobly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived</hi> for her Husband's ſake, Treated with Airs, Balls, Banquets, and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pretty little <hi>Frolicks</hi> and <hi>amorous Gambals,</hi> not fit to be here mentioned: All her <hi>Lovers</hi> are now met together, like Flies in Summer, every one intending to have a <hi>lick</hi> at her <hi>Honey-pot;</hi> every one putting forward, as he finds opportunity. One <hi>Complements</hi> her at a very Modiſh rate; the other <hi>Preſents</hi> her with a rich Diamond; one gives her the gentle <hi>Tread</hi> on the Toe, <hi>en paſſant,</hi> as the <hi>Frenchman</hi> hath it; the other gives her the <hi>amorous Squeeze</hi> of the hand; another leaning diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondently upon his Elbow, reaches her with a <hi>languiſhing Eye;</hi> So that ſhe muſt needs be void of all Senſe, if ſhe depart without <hi>underſtanding</hi> all their <hi>good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions.</hi> Thus every Spark endeavours (as much as in him lies) to make her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band bear the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Enſign of Chriſtian Matrimony in the Van; which at laſt proves the occaſion of her <hi>ſhame</hi> and his <hi>ſorrow;</hi> for either by the mis-manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or miſ-timing of her <hi>Amorous De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns,</hi> or the diſcovery of her <hi>Frolicks</hi> by ſome ſpecial Friend or Relation, the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band comes to <hi>underſtand</hi> the whole
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109001:17"/> Truth, and nothing but the Truth, which drives him into a ſtrange <hi>Paroxyſm</hi> of Profound <hi>Melancholy,</hi> that all the Helle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore among the <hi>Anticyrae</hi> can never <hi>reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> him: if he attempt to <hi>ſtrike</hi> her, that won't do, but only add fuel to her Fire; that will take off her <hi>Affection,</hi> ſo that ſhe will never <hi>dally</hi> with him, but only to paſs away the time for want of <hi>better Company,</hi> and make uſe of him only as a <hi>Cloak</hi> to ſhrowd and conceal her <hi>Laſcivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</hi> Thus is the poor Gentleman ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the <hi>Second Matrimonial Solace,</hi> being now faſt bound to <hi>Ixion</hi>'s Wheel of Miſery, where he muſt live in a moſt <hi>laguiſhing,</hi> and die in a very <hi>miſerable</hi> Condition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="comment">
               <head>The Third COMFORT. The Bonny Girl, Twatling Goſſips, and Contented Drudge.</head>
               <p>THE Youngſters of this <hi>Wanton</hi> Age, are ſo high-fed, live ſo much at eaſe, their Blood is ſo <hi>plentiful</hi> and <hi>ſprightly,</hi> that they cannot contain themſelves long without an <hi>Evacuation</hi> of the Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies of the <hi>Fourth Concoction,</hi> and ſo muſt take a Wife (the Remedy often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times proving <hi>worſe</hi> than the Diſeaſe)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109001:17"/> and <hi>eagerly purſue</hi> their own Miſery and Diſcontent; for our young Couple being Married, at the uſual time the <hi>Teeming</hi> Bonny Girl <hi>grows big,</hi> tho poſſibly (as it too frequently falls out) not by the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Father; and now he begins to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the <hi>Miſery, Trouble</hi> and <hi>Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of a wedded Life; now muſt the poor Fellow <hi>trot</hi> all about the Town on his <hi>Wife's Errands,</hi> to purchaſe all things that may pleaſe her, if poſſible; for ſhe begins to be <hi>ſquemiſh,</hi> her Stomach fails, grows weak and peeviſh, like her ſelf, and nothing will <hi>down</hi> with her but what is of the <hi>beſt;</hi> now he muſt trudge about night and day, ranſack Heaven and Earth for <hi>Delicacies</hi> to cheriſh and comfort her, and empty his <hi>Purſe</hi> to fill her <hi>Paunch</hi> with Dainties; and this pleaſant life muſt be led for ſix or ſeven Moneths together, while his Wife <hi>Pampers</hi> her Carcaſs at home, and can ſcarce get a good word for his pains (a poor <hi>Gratuity</hi> for his kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) nay probably, complains ſhe is not ſo <hi>carefully provided for,</hi> as other Women in her Condition; altho the poor Man riſes early, goes to Bed-late, and eats the Bread of <hi>Carefulneſs,</hi> contriving all ways poſſible, for the <hi>proviſion</hi> of his Family; but this is not all, the time of her <hi>falling
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109001:18"/> in pieces</hi> draws near, and here the poor Fellow is expoſed to a <hi>world</hi> of <hi>Charge</hi> and <hi>Trouble;</hi> out he muſt to procure God-fathers and God-mothers, and ſuch as ſhe <hi>approves</hi> of too, for in this he is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd the freedom of his <hi>own Election</hi> the Midwife muſt be fetcht, dry and we Nurſes provided (a ſort of <hi>chargeable Slut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> who will <hi>lap</hi> up more <hi>good Liquor</hi> in on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> day, than the good Husband ſwallows i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a whole Week) in ſhort, her Throes com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> very thick upon her, and ſhe is ſurrounde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with a <hi>Crew</hi> of <hi>Goſſiping Neighbours<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> the Good-man in the mean time is at h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Devotion</hi> for her ſafe Delivery, which being over, then all his Care is to plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Woman in the Straw,</hi> and her Twa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Companions, who eat and drin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>merrily,</hi> and he ſpares no coſt to entertai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them, and if any thing <hi>diſpleaſes</hi> them 'tis forty to one, but one of the Goſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtarts up and ſays, in troth, Mrs. I do v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much <hi>wonder,</hi> and ſo does all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Company, that your <hi>Husband</hi> takes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> more <hi>care</hi> of <hi>you</hi> and <hi>your</hi> Child, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally being your <hi>Firſt-born;</hi> what wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he do, I trow, had you five or ſix? ſay another, I'll aſſure you, if my Husban<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould <hi>ſerve me</hi> ſo, I would ſtudy Nigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Day to be <hi>reveng'd</hi> of him; Indee
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109001:18"/> ſays a third, I would not have you put up this <hi>Affront</hi> patiently; for if he ſerves you thus at the firſt, his uſage will be <hi>cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer</hi> to you hereafter. Couſin, ſays a fourth, I admire, that you, being ſo <hi>diſcreet</hi> a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and of a <hi>good Family,</hi> that you can endure his unworthy <hi>behaviour</hi> to you, eſpecially in this weakly condition: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las! replies the Wife, I know not what to do with him, he is ſo <hi>croſs</hi> and <hi>unkind</hi> to me. Upon my word, ſaith the other, he is an <hi>ill-natur'd Man,</hi> that he is not here in perſon to attend on this good company: Then ſtarts up a <hi>Bold, Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Houſewife,</hi> and thus begins to chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; All the Neighbours here know very well, it was a <hi>common Rumour</hi> of my Husband, that he was the <hi>untowardeſt</hi> Man in the World, and would often threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to <hi>break my bones,</hi> and be the death of me; but I thank my Stars for it, and my undaunted Spirit together, that I have <hi>tam'd</hi> him ſufficiently; I have brought him now to that paſs, that he dares as well eat his Nails, as <hi>do</hi> any thing to <hi>diſoblige</hi> me. 'Tis very true, when we were <hi>firſt Married</hi> he began to be Lofty and Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert, but I pluckt up a <hi>good Spirit,</hi> ſet my foot in the <hi>Stirrup,</hi> rode him with a <hi>Bit</hi> and a <hi>Snaffle,</hi> till I quite tired; and cur'd
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109001:19"/> him of his <hi>Reſty, Skittiſh Humour:</hi> inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that he has confeſt, there is <hi>no good to be done</hi> with me by foul means: nay, if he had kill'd me, I was reſolv'd never to <hi>Truckle</hi> under him; and now I can <hi>ſay, and do</hi> what I Pleaſe, without the <hi>leaſt contradiction;</hi> for I will have the laſt word, right or wrong; ſo that now he croſſes the Cudgels to me, and <hi>ſubmits:</hi> nay, I will aſſure you Gentlewomen, there's no man living, how <hi>perverſe</hi> ſoever, but his Wife may bring him to be <hi>Complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant,</hi> if ſhe take right meaſures, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage him with Diſcretion; therefore, pray Neighbour, when your <hi>Husband</hi> comes Home, ring him ſuch a Peal as may make his Ears glow, and his Heart ake, or you'll never <hi>get the better</hi> on him as long as you have a day to live. Thus theſe Goſſiping Baggages, having cloy'd 'emſelves with good Wine, and <hi>plentiful Chear,</hi> abuſe the poor Man for his Pains, and by their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice ſet the Husband and Wife at <hi>vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</hi> the <hi>Curſe</hi> of parting Man and Wife light on them for their pains. Well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus gorged with Edibles and Pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, away they go, and leave the Woman to <hi>play her part</hi> according to their goodly Inſtructions. At length Home the Husband returns, having undergone the <hi>Drudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:109001:19"/> of the Day with Care and Pains, and no ſooner enters his own Doors, but enquires how his Wife does; the Nurſe, like an <hi>Inſtructed</hi> Diſſembling Slut, makes anſwer, that ſhe is in a very <hi>weak condition,</hi> and this bout had like to have coſt her Life; I have tended ſeveral in my time, but your Wife is the <hi>weakeſt Woman</hi> I ever look'd to in all my Life; thus they Teaze the fooliſh Man, who cannot reſt till he hath ſeen his Wife; into the <hi>Chamber</hi> he goes, and the firſt Salutation is, how is't my Dear? Truly Love, very ſick and weak; I am very ſorry for it; and fear you <hi>faſt</hi> too much: I cannot eat, my Appetite is Pall'd and gone: Well, I will order you ſome <hi>Gelly-broths</hi> and <hi>Caudles</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort you; which he does accordingly, and ſends 'em to her: Thus tir'd with running about all day long, he calls for ſome <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment,</hi> which is brought him, being only the <hi>Reverſions</hi> of the Servants, which he is content with, whilſt his Wife is cheriſh'd with <hi>coſtly</hi> and <hi>comfortable</hi> Draughts, he only ſwells his empty Maw, with Flatulent and Sower <hi>Sixes,</hi> and to Bed he packs up with his Head full of care and ſleep; in the Morning up he gets by Break of Day, <hi>viſits</hi> his Wife, and asks her how ſhe <hi>reſted;</hi> alas! (ſaith ſhe) I
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109001:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:109001:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:109001:21"/> have not ſo much as <hi>cloſed</hi> my eyes, or had one <hi>wink</hi> of ſleep all this Night, tho ſhe reſted as well and ſoundly as if ſhe had taken a Doſe of <hi>Opium.</hi> My Heart, ſaith he, the <hi>Goſſips</hi> will be here to day, you muſt <hi>make much</hi> of them, and ſhould think of riſing to <hi>entertain</hi> them; for you have kept your Bed above a Fortnight; Love we muſt be as <hi>ſaving</hi> as we can, Charges are great, and I have much ado to keep both ends together. Think of Riſing! (ſays the Wife) a Curſe on the Hour I was born! O, that I had <hi>died in Labour,</hi> and then there had been an end of me! Is it come to this indeed; muſt I riſe alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and am not able to ſtand upon my Leggs? Do you long to ſee me <hi>drudging about the Houſe</hi> before I am able to creep? You are a very <hi>kind</hi> Man, a moſt <hi>loving</hi> Husband indeed; I find now you wiſh me dead, ſo do I too. Well! well! I am content to riſe to Morrow, come on't what will; I do very well foreſee what I muſt <hi>undergo</hi> for the time to come; what would you do, if I had ten or twelve Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, which <hi>God forbid,</hi> and if it be his will, I hope this is the laſt? but Gods will be done. As for Goſſips coming to ſee me, I had rather they would ſtay at Home, and ſo they would if they knew how
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109001:21"/> little their <hi>Viſits</hi> pleaſe me; nor would you your ſelf (if you had any reſpect for me) <hi>promote</hi> their coming, when here were Twenty <hi>Diſcreet Women</hi> at leaſt, who came to ſee me with a great deal of <hi>Kindneſs</hi> and <hi>Reſpect,</hi> and the Chear you provided for them, I would be aſhamed to ſet before their <hi>Servants;</hi> this is truth, Sir, I ſaw it with my own eyes, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm'd with Tears, to hear that they ſhould in a <hi>ſlighting, ſcoffing way</hi> take notice of it. Well, My Dear, you are ſoon moved I find to <hi>Paſſion,</hi> tho I give you no <hi>occaſion;</hi> but ſatisfie your ſelf, that hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, I ſhall be content that you <hi>pleaſe your ſelf,</hi> and riſe when you think it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient. Do what you pleaſe, Sir, only I beg of you to talk to me <hi>no longer;</hi> for I am <hi>very full</hi> of Pain, and would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you to ſend to our Neighbours <hi>not to come</hi> becauſe I am ſo much <hi>indiſpoſed;</hi> Love, ſays he, they <hi>ſhall come,</hi> and be well treated too; for Gods ſake let me alone, and do what you will. Then one of the Nurſes attaques him with her <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful</hi> Tongue, pray Sir, do not <hi>force</hi> my Miſtreſs to ſpeak, it is very <hi>dangerous;</hi> for ſhe is a very <hi>weak</hi> Woman, and if the Wind gets into her Head, it will do her and <hi>irreparable Injury</hi> (O brave Doctreſſes!)
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109001:22"/> then ſhe <hi>draws</hi> the <hi>Curtains,</hi> and the <hi>Wife</hi> and the <hi>Husband</hi> are not yet Reconcil'd; however ſhe expects the <hi>Goſſips,</hi> who will act their parts ſo <hi>effectually,</hi> and give him ſuch Flouts and Jeers, which will ſo <hi>tame</hi> him, that he may be eaſily <hi>led</hi> any where by the <hi>Noſe</hi> for ever after. Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver away he goes and makes <hi>Proviſion</hi> for them in a more plentiful manner, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Reproof he received from his Wife. The Gentlewomen at the <hi>time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed</hi> appear, he welcomes them all, and <hi>conducts</hi> them to his <hi>Wife</hi>'s Chamber; where <hi>they</hi> and the <hi>ſick Woman</hi> Eat and Drink heartily, to a more than becoming Feſtivity, and <hi>Flirt</hi> and <hi>Joke</hi> with the Maſter of the Houſe, till they have quite <hi>diſpirited</hi> him, and made him a meer Mamma Mouchey; ſo that now he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to <hi>do any thing</hi> for a quiet Life, <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle</hi> the Brat in his Arms, <hi>dry</hi> the <hi>piſt Clouts</hi> on his Horns, for fear the <hi>Nurſe</hi> curſe him, or elſe his <hi>Wife</hi> (having got the better end of the Staff) tell him plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he ſhall <hi>never more enter</hi> her Premiſes. This <hi>comfortable Life</hi> he muſt lead; his Wife muſt be <hi>maintained</hi> at a high rate, and have her <hi>Will</hi> in all things; he muſt live <hi>Meanly</hi> and <hi>Penuriouſly,</hi> having his will in <hi>nothing;</hi> and thus he is caught in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109001:22"/> the <hi>Net,</hi> where he <hi>ſtruggles</hi> to no purpoſe, for there he <hi>muſt Live,</hi> in ſpight of Fate, <hi>Deſpicably,</hi> and die <hi>Wretchedly.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="comment">
               <head>The Fourth COMFORT. The decay'd Gentleman, the Virago and her Topping Daughters.</head>
               <p>WHen a Man hath been ſo <hi>Injurious</hi> to himſelf as to abandon a <hi>ſingle Life,</hi> and run <hi>headlong</hi> upon Marriage, without any Reaſon or Senſe; and having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ved in the <hi>ſtate of Matrimony</hi> for the pace of <hi>ten</hi> or <hi>twenty</hi> years, hath his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>ſurrounded</hi> with <hi>Children,</hi> and the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ack Ox</hi> hath <hi>trod</hi> upon his <hi>Foot,</hi> all that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e can do, is only to keep the <hi>Wolf</hi> from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e door, <hi>Charges</hi> daily increaſing; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mong them three or four Daughters <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ageable,</hi> but not as yet diſpoſed of, whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>od Qualities (I mean <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce</hi>) are too Notorious to the World, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the <hi>Father</hi> hath little, or no <hi>Portion</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> beſtow upon them; he, poor Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an, muſt be in a kind of <hi>Troubleſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ndition;</hi> for his Daughters muſt be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aintain'd <hi>gentilely</hi> at home, and <hi>well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tired</hi> when they go abroad <hi>a la Mode,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> theſe three Reaſons:</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:109001:23"/>
               <p>Firſt, That they may be the ſooner <hi>put off,</hi> and by their Mincing Gate, and Gay Garb, <hi>bait</hi> ſome <hi>Spark</hi> or other into the <hi>Net</hi> of <hi>Marriage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, if their Father be <hi>Hide-bound,</hi> and will not do it, he ſhall have his <hi>Hands</hi> and his <hi>Heart</hi> full, and they will do little or nothing for him, preſuming upon their <hi>Mother,</hi> who countenanceth them in ſo doing, like a <hi>dutiful Wife.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, the young Women in the Neighbourhood are maintained <hi>finely,</hi> and well habited, and ſo <hi>muſt they</hi> too, and why not, as well as <hi>other mens</hi> Children, of the ſame Rank and Quality?</p>
               <p>Thus is the Man <hi>wearied</hi> out of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Life, if he <hi>drudge</hi> not in the World to ſupport their <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Vanity,</hi> tho pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably to their utter Ruine: ſometimes he beats the hoof twenty or thirty Miles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>buſineſs,</hi> or, if he be Maſter of an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Horſe, rides at other times 100, to attend the <hi>Parliament,</hi> or <hi>Courts</hi> in Term-time about a <hi>Law-ſuit,</hi> which hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending from his <hi>Child-hood,</hi> ſo that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is forced, to ſave Charges, to go ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>meanly</hi> accoutred, having a pair of Boo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Nine or Ten Years <hi>old,</hi> and ſo often <hi>vamp'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>mended,</hi> that, like <hi>Drake</hi>'s Ship, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have not <hi>one piece</hi> of their <hi>firſt Materials</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:109001:23"/> his Spurs were made in <hi>Harry</hi> 8th's time, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd one of them wants the great gingling Rowel: his cloaths ſo mean and aged, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat they will ſcarce <hi>hang together</hi> by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſiſtance of Patching, ſo as to cover his Nakedneſs, or keep his body from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ury of the Weather: The Sword he years is a Hacking Morglay, which ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f his Anceſtors took at the Siege of <hi>Troy:</hi> His Beaſt carries behind him an <hi>old Knap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ick,</hi> that his Fore-fathers uſed at the Siege <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f <hi>Bouloigne;</hi> the Livery he gives is well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nown, for the <hi>Antiquity</hi> thereof, both in City and Country, the Coat being <hi>worn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhort</hi> that it ſcarce reaches the Pocket<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oles, and in good faith,'tis like to be long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nough, e're it be longer: in ſhort, thus he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ves <hi>ſparingly</hi> abroad, to balance the great <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xpences</hi> at Home, whither he returns, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith a <hi>heavy</hi> Heart, and a <hi>light</hi> purſe, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>awyers, Attorneys, Sollicitors and Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffs having ſufficiently <hi>purg'd</hi> his Bags, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d ſent him away with a <hi>Flea</hi> in his Ear. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eing arrived at his own appartment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ld now his <hi>comfortable</hi> Reception, his <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd</hi> welcome by his Wife! who as ſoon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhe eſpies him, inſtead of Embracing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eats him with a <hi>ſower Countenance,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ds fault with ſome <hi>miſcarriage</hi> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſe, ſtamps and ſtorms like a <hi>Bethlemite,</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:109001:24"/> the Servants being all at her Beck, dare not give any <hi>Reſpect</hi> or <hi>Attendance:</hi> nay, the good-natur'd Elf, dares not <hi>open his mouth</hi> for any thing, till the Storm is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, bears all patiently, without the leaſt noiſe, to prevent <hi>diſturbance</hi> in his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſets him down ſome diſtance from the Fire, tho very <hi>cold,</hi> ſhe and her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren keeping all the <hi>heat</hi> from him; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> length being moved with her Dogged and Curriſh Uſage toward him, he may ſay, Methinks Miſtreſs, you look very <hi>ſurly</hi> upon me, as if I had offended you, pray get me ſomewhat to <hi>refreſh</hi> me, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> am almoſt <hi>ſpent</hi> and <hi>tir'd</hi> off of my Legs being wet to the skin, having neither <hi>Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> nor <hi>Drunk</hi> this day, and yet you cannot ſo much as afford me a <hi>pleaſant</hi> look: Yes ſaith ſhe, I had need <hi>take care</hi> of you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, you have <hi>ſpun a fair Thread,</hi> I have loſt more by my Hemp and Flax ſince your abſence, than you will <hi>get</hi> theſe <hi>fiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> years,</hi> by taking your Man along with you, ſo that I had no body to <hi>help me</hi> to Soak or Whiten it; beſides, I have often wiſh'd you, ſince your <hi>departure,</hi> at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Devils Arſe of Peak, that you did not <hi>ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> the <hi>holes</hi> in the Hen-houſe, for the ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pole-Cat hath eaten three of my be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Laying Hens, whoſe loſs is not ſo inconſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:109001:24"/> as you imagine, and if you ſteer his Courſe, you will be certainly one of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <hi>pooreſt Men</hi> in your Family: Pray, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith he, Miſtreſs, don't you give me ſuch Language, God be praiſed, I am <hi>content</hi> with what I have, and ſhall have more if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be his will, beſides, there are ſtill ſome <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>haritable,</hi> good People in my Family: <hi>Good,</hi> for what, ſays ſhe, for <hi>nothing?</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> know but few of them, if any, worth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he mentioning: Ay, ſaith the Husband, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y good People: And <hi>what good</hi> do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey do you? what good? as <hi>much good</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s yours: ſay you ſo, ſweet Sir, but I'll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e bold to <hi>tell you</hi> to your Teeth, and <hi>ſpit</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the face of thoſe that ſhall dare to <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſe</hi> it, that yours had been a <hi>poor ſtock,</hi> had it not been for the frequent <hi>Supplies</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny Friends and Relations, and if they ſhould hear you ſay half ſo much to me, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey would tell you your own, in good Faith, would they. Well! prethee ſweet heart (ſaith he) be not ſo High, let us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eave off this Diſcourſe: and ſo he is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed to acquieſce, for fear his Friends ſhould be acquainted therewith. But the Fray is not yet over, for it happens that one of the little Children falls a <hi>crying,</hi> and as it falls out, 'tis the Father's <hi>Darling,</hi> whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he whips ſeverely, more to <hi>ſpite him,</hi> than
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:109001:25"/> any thing elſe; prethee Woman, ſait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he, why are you ſo <hi>ſharp</hi> with the Child in the Devil's name, ſaith ſhe, what d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you <hi>concern</hi> your ſelf, you are not at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> trouble of <hi>bringing</hi> them up, or <hi>lookin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> after them? that is my Drudgery Nigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and day, as long as I am able to ſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon my legs; ſhame on you, muſt I b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thus controul'd, that I muſt not <hi>correct</hi> my own Child? if I take him up agen, I'll fle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him, and do you ſeek your remedy. The ſays the Nurſe, indeed Sir, you are not a home to <hi>ſee it,</hi> nor do you know what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>world<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>heavy hand</hi> my Lady has in bringing them up: by my faith (ſaith the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bermaid) it is a ſtark ſhame, that whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you come home, inſtead of our <hi>rejoycing</hi> at your Company, you create nothing bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Diſturbance</hi> and <hi>Noiſe</hi> among us; Noiſe ſaith the Lady, go you Fool, this is no thing in compariſon of what I have taken at his hands, and muſt do ſo ſtill, as long as it pleaſeth my good God. Thus the whole Family, by the inſtigation of the Miſtreſs, is up in Arms againſt their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, who <hi>creeps</hi> to Bed Supperleſs and Comfortleſs, the Children in the Night bawling about his ears, that he can take no reſt, which is done on purpoſe to diſturb him; thus he ſpends his <hi>days</hi> in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:109001:25"/> Care, his <hi>Nights</hi> in Torment; and ſo we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave him to enjoy the Fruits of his Folly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="comment">
               <head>The Fifth COMFORT. The Doting Cornuto, and Young Brisk Girl.</head>
               <p>LOve or Luſt, call it what you pleaſe, may be counted (if at all) <hi>pardona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le</hi> in Young; but in Old Men not to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndur'd; when they have exhauſted their <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umidum radicale,</hi> their Bodies being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aded by Rheum, and thoſe many <hi>Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ities</hi> that attend Old Age. This is the Caſe at preſent of our <hi>Grave Senior</hi> who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> married to a Young Brisk Girl of a <hi>Nobler extract</hi> than himſelf; but certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y there is reaſon in this, for ſhe might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave been Matcht to a far <hi>greater advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>age,</hi> but her Friends were forced to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe of her to any one (God wot) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng but of a <hi>crackt Reputation,</hi> and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng had a ſhrewd <hi>Miſchance,</hi> the effect of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er Youthful Wantonneſs; and tho this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath been frequently diſcours'd of about <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Town, yet the <hi>doting</hi> Cornuto, is too Credulous to believe any ſuch Rampant Stories, but ſtands highly in her <hi>Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Thus he, being well ſtricken in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:109001:26"/> years, abandons all ſorts of Pleaſures, and only ſtudies to <hi>turn the Penny</hi> to advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, that he may maintain her according to her port, Gentilely: but his Lady be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a <hi>Generous Temper,</hi> and in the Vigour of her Youth, is no way incline<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to that <hi>cloſe-fiſted</hi> humour of her A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varicious Bedfellow, but reſolved to paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> her time <hi>jovially,</hi> and ſwim in <hi>Deligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>Pleaſure.</hi> To this purpoſe her firſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Intrigue is to get a <hi>Gallant,</hi> which is ſoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> done by the <hi>opportunities</hi> She has at Treat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Meetings, whither She daily <hi>rambles,</hi> and an <hi>Aſſignation</hi> being made, they ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſs and embrace one another without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul or Suſpicion; for her <hi>Honour</hi> muſt be ſtill preſerved <hi>untainted;</hi> and having diverted themſelves with all the Amorous Sports and Love-Toys, that <hi>Wantonneſs</hi> ever could invent, the next Diverſion is to Droll at her <hi>Aged Husband,</hi> who is buffooned on all ſides by all Perſons, but more <hi>particularly</hi> and <hi>bitterly</hi> by her La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhip. Well! home ſhe returns, big with <hi>expectation</hi> of her Gallants appointed <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit</hi> the next Morning, and to Bed with her Husband She goes, with as much love as the Devil has for Holy Water; and by that time his <hi>frozen Limbs</hi> are ſomewhat thaw'd with <hi>natural heat,</hi> the Cuckoldly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:109001:26"/> Goat muſt be up and <hi>at her;</hi> but ſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends She is very ill, drowſie and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to ſleep; therefore <hi>pray</hi> (ſaith She) <hi>let me alone,</hi> you will infinitely oblige me, if you will <hi>forbear</hi> till Morning, and then I ſhall be fit for your ſervice; at which the Old Oaf turns for fear of <hi>diſpleaſing her;</hi> whoſe head runs upon nothing but <hi>Meeting</hi> with her <hi>Friend,</hi> and contrives withal, (conſulting with her Pillow) how to <hi>put off</hi> the Old Man, that he ſhall not <hi>touch her,</hi> when Morning comes; which ſhe cunningly effects, as followeth; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ither ſhe <hi>riſes</hi> very <hi>early,</hi> leaves the old Gentleman faſt (for <hi>Age</hi> is Childiſh, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onſequently <hi>ſleepy</hi> for the moſt part) and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <hi>ſatisfied</hi> or <hi>tired</hi> with her Gallant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore Father <hi>Graybeard</hi> awakes: and then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ummageth about the Houſe, playing the Good Houſewife ſeemingly: or otherwiſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he does not <hi>riſe at all;</hi> but before day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ears, ſhe <hi>ſighs</hi> and <hi>groans</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> purpoſe, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he good Gentleman may <hi>hear</hi> her, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reſently asks her <hi>how ſhe is:</hi> indeed love, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith ſhe, I have ſuch a <hi>pain in my ſide,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccompanied with the <hi>Gripes,</hi> that I can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake no reſt, I think it is my old Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er: prethee, ſweet heart, turn to me: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon my faith, my Dear, I am all in <hi>a ſweat,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd <hi>dare not</hi> for fear of <hi>catching cold,</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:109001:27"/> which may <hi>coſt me my life,</hi> being of a weak Conſtitution: then he covers her cloſe up, bids her <hi>be careful</hi> of her ſelf, and he will <hi>take care</hi> of her Houſhold Affairs: up he gets without Fire or Candle, yet procures her a <hi>fire</hi> againſt <hi>her riſing:</hi> thus ſhe takes her eaſe, and laughs in her ſleeve at the Old Man's Folly; when he underſtands ſhe is up, he <hi>comes to ſee her</hi> very lovingly, and begins to be <hi>Amorous,</hi> but ſhe having a mind to <hi>diſappoint</hi> him, ſays, would it were God's Will that you would never <hi>meddle</hi> with me, till I did <hi>ask you:</hi> and would you not then, ſays he? no, upon my <hi>Conſcience,</hi> Love, I think not, and had I known but as <hi>much before,</hi> I would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have Married: Why then did you Marry, ſaith he? indeed <hi>Love,</hi> I know not I was but a <hi>Young Girl,</hi> and did it in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the <hi>Commands</hi> of my Parents what is the <hi>meaning</hi> on't, ſweet heart, you are always, in <hi>this humour?</hi> I do not know, but indeed, love, were it not to <hi>pleaſe you,</hi> I would never be troubled with <hi>due Benevolence,</hi> as you call it: thus ſhe wheedles the <hi>ſuperannuated Fop</hi> into a ſtrange conceit of her <hi>Chaſtity:</hi> ſo tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this perſwaſion increaſeth the <hi>Flome</hi> of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Affection, which he thinks can never b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> extinguiſhed. But now obſerve the <hi>damn'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:109001:27"/> ſubtilty</hi> of a wily Woman, who never wants one contrivance or other to <hi>chouſe</hi> any one ſhe hath a mind <hi>to pleaſe.</hi> If ſhe has a mind to Cajole him out of Cloaths, Rings, Jewels, Moneys, or <hi>any thing</hi> that ſhe <hi>fancies,</hi> the Scene is quite alter'd; then, when they are both warm in Bed, how the diſſembling Gipſie <hi>Kiſſes, Hugs</hi> and <hi>Squee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es him</hi> in her Arms, till his old bones <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>attle in his skin, and helps his <hi>aged Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſs</hi> with her <hi>youthful Activity,</hi> ſo that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he old Man is in a kind of Extaſie, to find <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er ſo <hi>prodigal of her Favour</hi> and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſs; prethee my Dear! (ſaith ſhe) have a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reat <hi>care</hi> of <hi>your ſelf,</hi> for my ſake, as well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s your own; for my life is bound up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith yours, and one grave muſt contain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s both: Would to God I had no other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aradiſe on <hi>this ſide Heaven,</hi> but to be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbed in <hi>your Arms,</hi> this I ſpeak cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly, God is my Witneſs; and if any Man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d ever touch <hi>my Lips,</hi> but your ſelf, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Couſin, (and you allow of that by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmanding me <hi>to do it,</hi>) then let my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uniſhment be never to receive Kiſs or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbrace from you more, and that I am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e would ſoon <hi>break</hi> my <hi>poor Heart;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I am confident there is not a <hi>ſweeter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atured</hi> Man in the Univerſe, than <hi>you</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c. No, Love, ſaith he, <hi>except</hi> the <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:109001:28"/> that Courted you before me: Piſh Piſh, ſays, ſhe, upon my Honour, I was <hi>ſmitten with you</hi> the firſt time I ſaw you, tho at a diſtance, I may very ſafely ſwear it was <hi>Love at firſt ſight;</hi> I think it was a <hi>Match made in Heaven;</hi> for my Father would have Married me to that Gentleman, but I would never <hi>conſent</hi> to it; I can give no reaſon for it, but it was <hi>Decreed</hi> it ſhould be ſo. Thus ſhe <hi>procures</hi> what ſhe <hi>deſigned,</hi> tho at never ſo dear a rate, and this kind of <hi>Careſſing</hi> ſoon opens the <hi>Miſer</hi>'s <hi>Coffers,</hi> who knows her temper ſo well, that ſhe will never <hi>give over</hi> till ſhe <hi>has her will,</hi> whatſoever it coſts. Now ſhe begins, being <hi>furniſhed,</hi> to think o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> other things; her Gallant, that ſhe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly <hi>maintained,</hi> muſt like her overwor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Apparel, be <hi>laid aſide,</hi> and a new, rich on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>embraced;</hi> but ſhe is too crafty to be to forward, and <hi>keeps him</hi> at a bay for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> time, refuſeth his Preſents and Viſits, ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> her <hi>Plots</hi> are brought <hi>to Maturity:</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> young Gentleman is Enamoured, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wants an <hi>opportunity</hi> to meet with he Maid, which he ſoon obtains: Sweet-hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quoth he, I muſt have a <hi>little Talk</hi> wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you; that <hi>you may,</hi> Sir, if you pleaſe: yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> know (ſaith he) the <hi>extream paſſion</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I have for your Lady, do you think the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:109001:28"/> is any poſſibility of <hi>obtaining</hi> my deſires? Did ſhe ever <hi>mention me</hi> ſince the laſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terview? In truth, Sir, ſhe never opens her Lips, but to <hi>your commendation,</hi> and I am ſatisfied ſhe <hi>wiſhes</hi> you well: Well, Child! I do wholly confide in you, do but have me <hi>ſo much</hi> in your <hi>thoughts,</hi> as now and then to ſpeak a <hi>good word</hi> for me, and you ſhall be no <hi>loſer</hi> by it; I will beſtow a <hi>new Gown</hi> upon you, and here are <hi>five Guineys</hi> to buy you Gloves: Excuſe me, Sir, ſaith ſhe, I ſhall <hi>not take</hi> them; but indeed, Sweet-Heart, <hi>you ſhall,</hi> and ſo at length, with ſome little per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, like a right Maid, ſhe cryes <hi>Nay,</hi> and <hi>takes it:</hi> Away ſhe haſtens to her Lady, and acquaints her, that ſhe had met with her Gallant: well, and what ſays he? Why, faith, Madam, I think he is a little Lunatick upon <hi>your account,</hi> for he neither knows what he does or ſays: But how doſt <hi>thou like</hi> him, Girl? good Faith, Madam, I look upon him to be the moſt Comely, Complete Gentleman that ever I ſet my eye on in my Life, and I am of Opinion, that he will be a <hi>very Fond</hi> and <hi>Faithful</hi> Lover: nay, he is a Gentleman every Inch of him, hath a very good E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and is able to <hi>Gratifie</hi> your Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, by which Means you may embrace
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:109001:29"/> a Happy and Comfortable Piece of Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as long as you have the <hi>enjoyment</hi> of each others <hi>Society.</hi> In troth I am at a loſs, almoſt at my Wits end, I can <hi>get nothing</hi> out of my Husband, but what is <hi>abſolutely neceſſary:</hi> Pray, Madam, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of it, for I promiſed to <hi>return him an anſwer</hi> to morrow: But how, Girl, shall we <hi>curry</hi> this Horſe? how ſhall we <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage</hi> this Affair? As for that, Madam let me alone, I beſeech you, I ſhall meet him to Morrow-morning, and then I'll tell him plainly, that you <hi>would not</hi> ſo much as <hi>lend the leaſt Ear</hi> to my Diſcourſe, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to any thing requeſted (do what I could) being <hi>ſo tender</hi> of your Honour and Reputation, and I am ſure I can Act a Diſſembling Part pretty well. In the Morning, after ſhe had made him <hi>attend two hours</hi> at leaſt, they meet together ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Appointment. How now Sweet Heart, ſays the Gallant, how <hi>is it</hi> with your Lady? She is very Thoughtful and Penſive, full of Grief and Sorrow for the <hi>ill Uſage</hi> of her Husband, who is ſo wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Man to her, that it is not to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved what the <hi>Poor Gentlewoman</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoes: I am <hi>ſorry for't</hi> (<hi>quoth</hi> he) with all my Heart; but what did your Lady ſay to you? upon my Faith, Sir, I
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:109001:29"/> ſpake to her, for which I have gained a great deal of ill Will; ſhe would not ſo much as hear me, nor <hi>conſent</hi> to any thing propos'd, ſo highly doth ſhe <hi>prize her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation,</hi> and if ſhe had a mind to be <hi>kind</hi> to her Neighbours, and love them as her ſelf, ſhe is under an <hi>Italian</hi> ſlavery, being ſo <hi>kept in</hi> and <hi>Watcht</hi> by the old Lump of Jealouſie her Husband. I do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that ſhe ever <hi>exchanged</hi> a word with any Man in Diſcourſe, ſince I have waited upon her, and I have been her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant theſe <hi>four years</hi> and upwards, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with <hi>your ſelf</hi> the other day, whom ſhe remembers ſtill, and for ought I know, to be plain with you, would <hi>ſooner love you,</hi> than any other in the World. Dear Child, (ſaith he) bring but that about, and I'll be your Eternal Friend. Truly Sir (ſaith ſhe) I <hi>have done</hi> already all that <hi>lies in my power</hi> as to that, and dare not attempt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further, but in <hi>any thing</hi> elſe feaſeable, Command me, and I'm your Servant. Prethee, adviſe me what to do in this Caſe: Why, your beſt way will be to make <hi>an Addreſs</hi> to her your ſelf, and now is the moſt Critical time in the World; for <hi>ſhe</hi> and <hi>her Husband</hi> are at Variance, and you will find her at Church, where you may make your Amours to her, Careſs
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:109001:30"/> her, and <hi>preſent her,</hi> tho I'm confident ſhe'll refuſe all; but no matter for that, ſhe'll have a <hi>great eſteem</hi> for you, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding her Denial, and will ſet a higheou value upon <hi>your Generoſity</hi> and <hi>Worth</hi> than you can poſſibly imagine, do as I counſel you, and ſo <hi>all happineſs</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend you. (Sanctified Advice indeed in ſo <hi>Sanctified a Place,</hi> to make the Church a <hi>Brothel-Houſe,</hi> and Religion a <hi>Pander</hi> to fordid Luſt!) When you have acted your part, as I have told you, (ſaith this She-Emiſſary of the Devil) <hi>give me</hi> what you intend her as a Preſent, and I will ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the matter, that ſhe <hi>ſhall accept</hi> of it, or do my utmoſt <hi>endeavour,</hi> tho I loſe my labour. You ſay very well, my Dear Child! and ſo they part. Away runs this Gigling Baggage, and <hi>ſmiling</hi> at her Lady; upon my Soul, Madam, there are a great many Perſons in the World, who would <hi>wiſh</hi> for your <hi>Happineſs;</hi> for he is reſolv'd to Accoſt you, and diſcover his whole mind; now ſummon all your <hi>diſcretion</hi> together, let this be your <hi>dernier effort,</hi> as the <hi>Frenchman</hi> terms it; carry your ſelf <hi>ſtrangely</hi> to him, and hold him in ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe for a time; for you know, 'tis Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation makes a <hi>Bleſſing dear;</hi> but be ſure you be not ſo ſevere in your deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:109001:30"/> as to Daſh the Young Gentleman quite out of Countenance. Thus <hi>full freigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> with hopes, ſhe haſtens to Church, ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulated by Lechery, rather than Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; where arrived, her Gallant attacques her, but ſhe will <hi>conſent</hi> to <hi>nothing,</hi> nor accept of his Preſents; however ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertains him ſo <hi>favourably,</hi> that he may plainly diſcover her Affection to be <hi>more</hi> than <hi>ordinary:</hi> ſo they take leave with a light heart, and the Lady and her wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Gentlewoman Conſult how to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage the <hi>Buſineſs cleanlily</hi> without ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion: I am ſatisfied, Madam, ſaith her Maid, that he has a <hi>longing deſire</hi> to be <hi>wrapt up</hi> in your Embraces, and I will tell him my Maſter is gone into the Country for ſome time, and bring him the <hi>back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</hi> to your Chamber, in the deepeſt ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the Night, (the ſecureſt time for ſuch Secreſies) yet ſo that you ſhall ſeem to be altogether <hi>ignorant</hi> of my <hi>Deſign,</hi> and Counterfeit a <hi>real Paſſion</hi> for ſo ſtrange and unworthy a <hi>ſurpriſal,</hi> and withal ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint him that you will <hi>cry out,</hi> and call upon me, and what he <hi>preſents</hi> you with by <hi>my hands,</hi> do you obſtinately refuſe at firſt; Chide me for it before his face, preſs me to return it, but yet I hope you will have the grace at laſt to <hi>accept it,</hi> for
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:109001:31"/> in truth there is <hi>no dealing</hi> with Men, but by <hi>out-doing</hi> them in Female-Craft, the only weapons we have to defend our ſelves againſt that Sex. Now this cunning Wench finds out the Gallant, who asks her what News? In ſhort Sir (ſaith ſhe) not to Trifle away time, which is very precious, if I could prevail with her to <hi>accept</hi> the <hi>preſent</hi> you intend her, the Buſineſs would be done effectually, and to your ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the Gallant being <hi>raviſhed</hi> with her Diſcourſe, immediately puts <hi>fifty Guineys</hi> into her Hand, as a preſent of his Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to her Lady. Well Sir (ſaith ſhe) I will <hi>undertake</hi> one thing more, for I know my Lady has a kindneſs for you; therefore come you the <hi>back way,</hi> in the <hi>dead time</hi> of the Night, now my Maſter is abſent, and I will <hi>convey you</hi> to her Chamber, ſhe being <hi>Childiſh</hi> and conſequently <hi>Slee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py,</hi> you will have the better opportunity to <hi>uncloath</hi> your ſelf, and to Bed to her without Delay, or Ceremony, and in all probability the <hi>buſineſs</hi> will be done; for when you both are naked in one Bed, and in the dark too, there is no Diſpute of <hi>prevailing:</hi> come, come Sir! Women are Fleſh and Blood, as well as Men, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to <hi>Failings</hi> as well as they: I que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion not but you know the old Proverb,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:109001:31"/> 
                  <hi>Faint Heart ne'er won Fair Lady,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be Brisk and Active, and you need not deſpair of <hi>obtaining</hi> your deſire, I'll pawn my Reputation for it. The Lady is informed of all Paſſages between them, the <hi>Preſents are accepted,</hi> and the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-maid finds the <hi>Lover at the Place</hi> and Time appointed. Conveys him to her La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Chamber, and ſo <hi>leaves</hi> him: Now you may imagine that his Deſires being winged with Love, he was not long <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robing</hi> himſelf, but ſteals into Bed, and <hi>embraces</hi> her in his Arms, at which ſhe ſeems to <hi>ſtartle</hi> out of a feigned ſlumber, and ſays, what, my Dear, is it you? No, Madam, it is I, ſays the Gallant? how you? ſaith ſhe, who are you? this is not to be endured; whereupon ſhe ſtruggles to riſe, calls upon her Gentlewoman, twice or thrice, but alas! to no purpoſe: and great pity 'tis, that in <hi>ſuch a time</hi> of Neceſſity the Maid would give her no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: Ah! (ſaith ſhe) I'm betray'd, and ſtruggles for it, till her breath fail'd her, ſo that ſhe was at <hi>his mercy,</hi> who treated her very kindly, ſhe <hi>enjoying</hi> ſuch <hi>gentle uſage</hi> as ſhe <hi>expected,</hi> and they <hi>both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd;</hi> yet, to ſpeak the truth, Men are to blame for theſe rude Aſſaults: and what could a <hi>poor, weak</hi> Woman do alone, who
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:109001:32"/> durſt not <hi>cry out</hi> as loud as ſhe would, for fear of <hi>loſing</hi> her reputation? but to make the beſt of a bad Market, here's their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ſtill, the Curtains <hi>cannot,</hi> and the Maid <hi>dares not</hi> tell any Tales. Thus they made the beſt <hi>improvement</hi> of their time, and when they had ſufficiently <hi>ſolaced</hi> 'emſelves parted <hi>amicably,</hi> till they ſhould have an opportunity to re-enjoy their delights, the next Aſſignation. But at length by ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky accident or other, old <hi>Erra Pater,</hi> the Husband, comes to be <hi>certainly informed</hi> of the <hi>whole matter,</hi> and indeed more than he car'd to hear, which puts him into a Raving Jealous Fit of Melancholy, he <hi>ſtamps</hi> and <hi>ſtares</hi> like one diſtracted; but ſhe being now fleſhed with Luſt, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with <hi>impudence,</hi> gives him as good as he brings, upbraids him with his beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly Relations, laughs him to ſcorn, and this is the only Mirth he is like to enjoy with a <hi>continuando,</hi> till at laſt dried up with grief, and ſhrivel'd with Age, he brings his Gray hairs <hi>with ſorrow</hi> to the Grave.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="comment">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:109001:32"/>
               <head>The Sixth COMFORT. Jack-hold-my-ſtaff, and Lady Pouting.</head>
               <p>THE next Married Couple we meet with enjoy the <hi>Comforts of Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,</hi> as much as any of the five preceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: and here it is the <hi>fortune</hi> of a Man, to be Wedded to a Woman of ſo <hi>croſs</hi> and <hi>domineering</hi> a Temper, that ſhe will <hi>wear</hi> the <hi>Breeches</hi> and the <hi>Cap</hi> too, ſo that the poor Fop at Home is like <hi>John</hi> Hold-my-ſtaff, ſhe muſt Rule, Govern, Inſult, Brawl, <hi>underſtand all concerns</hi> at home and abroad, <hi>anſwer</hi> all buſineſſes, manage all Affairs, tho ſhe be never ſo well maintained, and want for nothing, yet he muſt be in the Family like a <hi>meer Cypher,</hi> and her whole delight and deſign is to <hi>Plague</hi> and <hi>Torment</hi> him. And thus ſhe begins; when they have paſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Night very <hi>ſportingly,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd the <hi>delights</hi> of the Marriage-Bed, as all good People ought to do, her Husband leaves her in a very good humour, to dreſs and trim her ſelf up, he, in the mean time, while ſhe is Tricking, <hi>takes care</hi> of the Domeſtick Affairs, and when Dinner is
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:109001:33"/> ready, ſends for his Wife to accompany him; but word is brought ſhe <hi>will not</hi> Dine to day, go agen (ſaith he) and bid her come, the Maid does ſo, and tells her Miſtreſs, my Maſter deſires you to come, go and tell him once more, that I <hi>will not</hi> come: the Good man is not ſatisfied with this anſwer, but ſends a <hi>third time,</hi> but to no purpoſe; ſo that at length he <hi>goes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> and asks her why ſhe will not come to Dinner? not a word will ſhe give him; what ail'ſt thou, my Dear? not a Syllable will ſhe return, but <hi>Pout</hi> and <hi>Frown,</hi> he inquires of the Family what is the reaſon, but cannot receive any <hi>ſatisfaction;</hi> when, as the truth is, ſhe ailes nothing, but only reſolves to be Dogged, and perhaps <hi>will not</hi> come to Dinner, do what he can; at other times, poſſibly he may prevail with her, when he hath begged ſo long till the meat is <hi>ſpoiled</hi> at the Fire, or <hi>cooled</hi> on the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and then he leads her to Dinner, but ſhe has no ſtomach, not one Morſel will go down, and he, like a Fop, to comply with her froward humour, <hi>will faſt</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, but the <hi>more fool</hi> he, for the more kindneſs he ſhews her, the more ſhe ſlights him; and, in my Opinion, ſhe is to be commended, for what need any Woman Court his favour, that doats upon her al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready?
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:109001:33"/> If he ſhould deſpiſe and contemn her, then ſhe had reaſon to ſcrue her ſelf into his <hi>affection,</hi> if poſſible. Another trick ſhe has to <hi>vex him,</hi> and that is this, when he is abroad, he ſometimes acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally meets with ſome of his <hi>intimate ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance,</hi> to whom he is infinitely obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and has a deſign to <hi>Treat them</hi> at his own Houſe, which is more Gentile, and leſs chargeable than at the Tavern; away he ſends his Servant to her, who when he comes, ſays, Miſtreſs, my Maſter will be here in the Evening with three or four Friends, Perſons of good Repute, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires you would <hi>provide</hi> every thing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for their reception. Upon my faith (ſaith ſhe) not I, I will have nothing to do with <hi>his Treats,</hi> why did he not come himſelf? I don't know that, Miſtreſs, but this he <hi>commanded</hi> me to tell you: Go, go, you are a very Rogue, and meddle with that, that does not <hi>concern you.</hi> Well, to ſhew her readineſs and obedience, ſhe firſt ſends all the Servants abroad, except a <hi>well-inſtructed</hi> Maid or two, brought up to her <hi>own hand,</hi> that have the <hi>length</hi> of her foot exactly, and then ſhe whips into her Chamber, and locks her ſelf up. When her Husband <hi>comes home,</hi> he asks if eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing be ready, according to his order;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:109001:34"/> truly Sir, ſaith the Maid, my Miſtreſs is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ill, and there is <hi>no body at home</hi> to do any thing; this puts our Maſter (if he may be ſo called without offence) into a great Chafe, but however <hi>leads his Friends</hi> into the Parlour, where <hi>all things</hi> are out of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and therefore goes to his Wife, why have you ſerved me ſo? ſaith he. Sir, you do <hi>command</hi> ſo many things at once, that I do not know which to <hi>turn my ſelf</hi> to firſt. Fy! Fy! ſaith he, you have done me the <hi>greateſt diskindneſs</hi> imaginable; for theſe are the only Perſons in the World, that I am <hi>obliged</hi> to. And how can I help it? (ſays ſhe) what would you have me to do? You ſhew your Wiſdom in it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; well, do what you pleaſe; I'm ſure it don't pleaſe me. But heark you, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, why did <hi>you ſend</hi> the Servants out of the way? God bleſs me, what a Queſtion is that from a <hi>wiſe Man</hi> as you are? Did I know, or could I divine, think you, that you had <hi>any occaſion</hi> for them? When the miſchievous Wretch ſent them out of the way, on <hi>purpoſe</hi> to diſappoint and Fret him. Away he goes agen to his Friends in a fury, but ſhe values it not, knowing the Storm will ſoon blow over. To be ſhort, he buſtles about, and ſets all things in as <hi>good order</hi> as he can. Then
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:109001:34"/> he ſends for ſome of the Table-Linnen, and word is brought <hi>there's none</hi> to be had. He goes to his Wife, and tells her what a ſhame and diſgrace it will be, both for him and her, not to have <hi>fine Linnen,</hi> ſhe tells him there is Linnen out already, <hi>good enough</hi> for them; for I'm ſure my Friends and Relations are content with it, when they beſtow a Viſit on us, and I'm ſure they are <hi>as good</hi> as the beſt of them, but however to ſatisfie you, all the beſt Linnen is in <hi>the Waſh,</hi> except what is under <hi>Lock and Key</hi> in the Trunk, and the Keys <hi>were loſt</hi> this Morning; but you had beſt go ask the Chamber-Maid, and bid her ſeek them; for I know not what is become of them, I have ſo <hi>many things running</hi> in my head, that I do not know ſometimes <hi>what I do,</hi> I am in ſuch diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and confuſion. Then the Fop bites the Lip, ſcratches his empty Nodle, and raps out a great Oath, being enraged (and cauſe enough too) that he will quickly make the <hi>Locks flie,</hi> if they do not find the Keys, and that ſpeedily too. Say you ſo, good Sir, quoth ſhe, I would I could <hi>ſee that</hi> once, you would ſhew a great deal of <hi>diſcretion</hi> in ſuch an action, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs; but his heat being ſomewhat allay'd, he conſiders ſhe is in the right, and ſo they
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:109001:35"/> fall to what is <hi>before them;</hi> the beſt Wine, Meat and every thing, being at <hi>her diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal,</hi> but they are like to go without it, for all her Huffing Husband. Nay, they muſt not have <hi>clean Sheets,</hi> but lie in <hi>Foul Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen.</hi> Well! in the Morning they take their leaves, and <hi>divert themſelves</hi> upon the Road with the Poor, over-ridden Fools affliction, reſolving <hi>never more</hi> to ſet <hi>foot</hi> within his doors. When they are gone, he attacques his Wife (thinking to beſtow a little <hi>moderate reproof</hi> upon her) ſaying, indeed, my Dear, you are a very ſtrange Woman, and I do not at all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand your <hi>froward humour:</hi> Lord bleſs me, ſaith ſhe, what ado you keep about me? I am weary of my Life, would I were as deep in the ground as I am high; I am <hi>up early,</hi> and <hi>down late,</hi> feeding your Poultry, looking after your Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Affairs, Spinning, Carding, and what not, never Idle, I am ſure the <hi>Care I take,</hi> will ſhorten my days; and yet all this does not deſerve (the more's my grief) ſo much as <hi>one good word</hi> from you, I <hi>ſcrape at home,</hi> and am as ſparing as can be, and you <hi>ſpend all abroad,</hi> yet you are not content. Thus they live a diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, wretched Life, <hi>old Age</hi> creeps up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, <hi>Grief</hi> ſeizeth him; he grows a
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:109001:35"/> 
                  <hi>Sot,</hi> and ſhe makes a <hi>Beaſt</hi> of him; he is intangled in the Net, and if he makes himſelf away, or comes to ſome ill End, he may <hi>thank himſelf</hi> for it, and verifies the old Proverb, <hi>Marriage and Hanging go by Deſtiny,</hi> and there is an end of him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="comment">
               <head>The Seventh COMFORT. The eaſie Fool, and Madam <hi>Wheedle.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Grave <hi>Italians</hi> have a Proverb, that <hi>Honeſt Men Marry, but Wiſe Men don't,</hi> and that is the Reaſon we have ſo many <hi>Fops</hi> in the World, and ſo few <hi>diſcreet</hi> Perſons. Our next Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Couple that we ſhall repreſent to you, we will ſuppoſe to be <hi>well Matcht,</hi> and they enjoy themſelves for ſome time; but the cleareſt Sun may be often <hi>overcaſt</hi> with Clouds, and then according to the <hi>Lyrick</hi> Poet,
<q>
                     <l>Deſinit in Piſcem Mulier formoſa ſupernè.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Fair</hi> Morning may end in a <hi>Lowring</hi> Evening. In the heat and vigour of Youth, their days may be ſomewhat Pleaſant;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:109001:36"/> but the Woman <hi>decays not ſo ſoon</hi> as the Man, let their condition be what it will, for he is often haraſſed and broken with <hi>Carking Care,</hi> whilſt ſhe grows plump with Delight and Pleaſure: And as for her Pain and Peril of <hi>Child-bearing,</hi> I do no more wonder at it, than at the laying of a great Egg, by a Hen, or a Gooſe, the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary <hi>effect of Nature,</hi> no more, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all their Tittle Tattle, the Hen being always the <hi>fatter</hi> for laying, whilſt the Cock <hi>ſcrapes</hi> and <hi>provides</hi> for her, as the honeſt Married Man for his Wife. And when the poor Man begins to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline,</hi> grow <hi>weak</hi> and <hi>imbecile,</hi> the good Wife continuing ſtill very <hi>Blithe</hi> and <hi>Gameſome,</hi> then the former Delights, Amorous Tricks, Kind Expreſſions, Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Looks and Glances, are turned into downright Scolding, and endleſs Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Well! at length ſhe begins to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover her <hi>good Temper,</hi> ſhe looks ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erly upon him with a Cloudy Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, <hi>ſlights</hi> and <hi>neglects</hi> him as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient, and is much concern'd at the <hi>Diſappointment</hi> of his Impetuous Nerve, his Heat and Activity being loſt, or at leaſt abated. Then ſhe grows of Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that God and the Laws did cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ordain a Woman <hi>more</hi> than one
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:109001:36"/> Man as well in <hi>England</hi> as in <hi>Turkey,</hi> and other well Regulated Countries, and ſaith ſhe will run the <hi>Riſque,</hi> and try how other Men are <hi>Weapon'd</hi> and Qualified for the Sport, and now the Game begins, ſhe grows worſe and worſe to him, leads him a <hi>ſad Life,</hi> that the fooliſh Man had better have choſen a Halter than a Wife, becauſe the former might have prov'd the <hi>end,</hi> whereas the latter is but the <hi>beginning</hi> of his Miſery: For now through her looſe courſe of Life, the Candle burns at <hi>both ends,</hi> they live at Rack and Manger (as the old ſaying is) and all tends to <hi>Ruine</hi> and <hi>Deſtruction,</hi> both of Soul and Body. Thus ſhe Conſumes with her <hi>unlawful Luſt,</hi> what he has Raked together by his <hi>lawful Care</hi> and <hi>Labour:</hi> Then he capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates with himſelf, and ſays, 'tis ſtrange to me that my Eſtate ſhould <hi>dwindle away</hi> at this rate, I am ſure, I have ever had a Care of the Main Chance, and paid every one their own, lived <hi>ſparingly,</hi> cloathed my ſelf <hi>meanly,</hi> and all to no purpoſe; for I can ſcarce keep the Wolf from the door. At length he grows <hi>Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous</hi> of his Wife, and <hi>imputes</hi> all his <hi>Misfortune</hi> to her Miſcarriage; but upon Examination of the whole, ſhe <hi>wheadles</hi> him ſo cunningly by her Woman-craft,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:109001:37"/> that he is ſatisfied thoſe <hi>Reports</hi> of her Immodeſty are <hi>falſe</hi> and malicious: She claps her hands upon his Head and wiſhes the Devil had all that is under her Hands, if ever <hi>any Man kiſt</hi> her but himſelf: and ſo the Fool is reconciled to his good Wife: Nay ſhe proceeds farther; As for that Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain that miſinformed you, ſince it muſt out, I'll tell you the <hi>whole truth</hi> of the Story; this Baſe, Perfidious Varlet hath been theſe two years <hi>attempting my Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity,</hi> but I have hitherto, (I thank my God for it) kept my ſelf Pure, Undefiled, and <hi>repulſed him</hi> to his ſhame, if he has any in him, notwithſtanding all his large Proffers and ſpecious Pretences. Can it enter into your thoughts, Sweet Heart! that I ſhould ever <hi>defile your Bed,</hi> away with all ſuch vain Imaginations! Can it be ſuppoſed, that I ſhould leave ſo <hi>kind</hi> and <hi>comely</hi> a Man as you are, for the Embraces of another? I were worſe than the Devil himſelf, if I ſhould take ſuch Helliſh Courſes; however I <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give</hi> him that has ſo baſely beſpattered me; but I muſt beg this Favour of you, that you never ſuffer him to <hi>ſet foot</hi> again within theſe doors; for if you do I will ſhun him <hi>Cane pejus &amp; angue,</hi> more than a curſt Gur, or a poiſonous Adder;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:109001:37"/> and I'll aſſure you, if I find you keep the leaſt Correſpondence with him for the future, I will <hi>pack up my Awls,</hi> be gone from you, and will never live with you while I have breath in my body: God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid that you ſhould ever live to ſee that day wherein I ſhould <hi>defile your Bed;</hi> no no, my Dear, it is not come to that yet, and then ſhe burſts outwith Tears, wring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her hands, and <hi>bitterly exclaiming</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that Wretch with all imaginable Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Invectives. Well! all is well; he is Baniſhed the Houſe, and the Good man rails againſt him for a <hi>great Rogue,</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe his <hi>good, Modeſt</hi> Wife in ſo high a Nature. Thus he grows fonder and fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, becomes a meer Aſs, is infatuated by his Wife, and transfigur'd into a Beaſt, without Senſe or Reaſon. Thus ſhe has <hi>got the Day,</hi> wears the Breeches (and thoſe Women are Fools that <hi>do not</hi> if they can) has <hi>freer acceſs</hi> to her Gallant, unſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, than formerly, and the Fop her Husband is deaf to all Accuſations: at length through this Dotage he falls into extream Penury, and finds to his Goſt, <hi>Sera eſt in fundo Parſimonia,</hi> 'Tis too late to be ſaving, when there is nothing to ſave; theſe are the <hi>Pleaſures</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts</hi> of a Married Life; he is made the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:109001:38"/> Scorn and Scoff of the Neighbourhood; ſome perhaps may be ſo kind as to <hi>pity the Honeſt Man;</hi> Wiſe Men reject him, and ſlight his Company; his Wife <hi>ſmiles</hi> at his Folly, enjoys her <hi>ſtolen Amours</hi> undiſcovered: grows at length as <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> as a Barber's Chair, no ſooner one is out, but another's in; expoſeth her Body to every Perſon, who is ſufficiently Tool'd for her Salaciouſneſs; and at laſt (as a juſt Reward of her, Debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Laſciviouſneſs) gets the <hi>Foul Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe</hi> of ſome Fouler Raſcal, gives it her good Husband, in Retaliation of all his <hi>fondneſs,</hi> ſo that they live in <hi>pain</hi> all the days of their lives, and at laſt end their days <hi>unpitied, loathſomely</hi> and <hi>wretchedly.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="comment">
               <head>The Eighth COMFORT. Father <hi>Noddy</hi> and Mother <hi>Snapp.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OUR next <hi>Married Couple</hi> that we are to diſcourſe of, are Perſons well enough Matched, if they could be <hi>content</hi> with what they have: God hath bleſt them with five or ſix <hi>ſweet Children</hi> Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:109001:38"/> and the Wife is as big as ſhe can Tumble with another. The time of her <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elivery,</hi> and his <hi>charges</hi> draws nigh, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>l things muſt be made ready for the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od Wives</hi> that are about her; at length <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fter ſome ſharp Throws, they give her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>er for dead, the poor Man is almoſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t his <hi>wits end,</hi> when he firſt hears that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſmal news, runs about like a Mad Man for help, <hi>falls on his knees,</hi> prays <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r her ſafe delivery, his Prayers are heard, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ſhe is brought to bed of a Luſty Boy. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow there is nothing but <hi>Carouſing</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ejoycing</hi> throughout the Family, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ap runs apace, but the Goſſips Tongues, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>l'd with Liquor, faſter, interlarded with <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nutty diſcourſe,</hi> ſuitable to the preſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>caſion. The Spring of the Year is now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ming on, and every one of any Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> is <hi>preparing</hi> for the Country to View <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atures Green Tapeſtry, and hear the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arbling Nightingale Carol her ſweet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>otes in the pleſant ſerenity of the quiet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vening, and among the reſt, the <hi>Wife <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſt go</hi> to take the Country Air after her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing in, and 'tis but requiſite for her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ealths ſake: but how to perſwade him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> take this Journy, there's the buſineſs. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow ſhe begins to ſet all Engines at work
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:109001:39"/> to that purpoſe; firſt ſhe comes home <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented,</hi> and is very Snappiſh to he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Husband; what's the matter? Love! ſaith he, what makes you ſo out of humour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the matter quoth ſhe, I think I have <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon enough,</hi> the Child is very much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered with a Violent Burning Feaver, inſomuch, that the Nurſe proteſts to me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (tho it was a long time 'ere I could get i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> out of her) that the <hi>poor Babe</hi> hath no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> taken the Breaſt theſe four days. I am heartily troubled, and know not how t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> help my ſelf; but that which afflicts me moſt is, that upon my conſcience, I believe God Almighty <hi>puniſhes the Child</hi> for <hi>my ſins,</hi> for I made a vow to go into the Country, and I ſhall never be at reſt, till I have <hi>performed</hi> it. Why, ſweet heart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaith he, have a little Patience, the time is not yet elapſed, you need not be ſo haſty: I have a great deal of <hi>buſineſs</hi> to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>diſpatch,</hi> and that of Concernment too now when that is over you ſhall go where you pleaſe. In troth, ſaith ſhe, don't tell me of buſineſs, I <hi>muſt go,</hi> and I <hi>will go,</hi> there's no neceſſity for my ſtay, I'm ſure I can do you no ſervice; and as for the <hi>charges,</hi> which I know is all your grie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and fear, I will pinch them out ſome way
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:109001:39"/> or other, tho I abate it in Houſe-keeping; This you do to perſwade the world what a <hi>good Husband</hi> you are; but if the truth were known, you will be found to <hi>ſave at the Spigot,</hi> and let it <hi>run out</hi> at the <hi>Bung-hole.</hi> The poor Man being thus Schooled by his Wife, muſt provide for this Journey, or elſe all the Fat's in the Fire; there will be no quietneſs, if ſhe does not go abroad. Well the time is come, and they muſt ſet forward. Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are provided, and a new <hi>Riding Garb</hi> for the Wife, he himſelf waits upon her, and muſt be as Tractable as a Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel upon the Road; his Wife is always wanting one thing or other; the Stirrup is <hi>too ſhort,</hi> or <hi>too long,</hi> the Pillion is not <hi>well fixt,</hi> her Scarf flies off; the Horſe Trots too hard, and makes her ſick, ſo that ſhe <hi>muſt light</hi> and take a Walk, then ſhe muſt be <hi>helpt up</hi> again, and this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary trouble hath the noddy brought upon himſelf, beſides the <hi>diſtillations</hi> that ſhe is troubled with every quarter of a Mile, ſhe having the Diabetes, and cannot hold water long. Being arrived at the place intended; ſhe is diſcompoſed with her Journey, and her ſtomach grows ſo nice, that it Kecks at ſuch Courſe food, as
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:109001:40"/> Beef and Mutton, and ſhe muſt have a <hi>Fowl</hi> to <hi>pick</hi> upon. Well away goes the contented Fool, and Trudges about the Town for ſome Dainty bit to pleaſe his Lady, coſt it never ſo much; for you know, <hi>far ſought,</hi> and <hi>dear bought</hi> is fit for <hi>ſuch Cattle;</hi> and when he comes home, if his Marketting diſpleaſeth her, then ſhe as well as the reſt of her Sex, falls fowl on the Good man, ſaying, <hi>in truth</hi> you are the ſtrangeſt perſon that ever liv'd, not at all fit to Travel; not at all Complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, you <hi>know not</hi> how to oblige our Sex. The Patient Fop hears all and bears all, being accuſtomed to ſuch kind of <hi>re-proof,</hi> as the Tinker's Dog is to carry the Budget. After they have ſolaced them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at this pleaſant rate, as long as ſhe thinks convenient, home they return, find all thing <hi>out of order,</hi> the Horſe dead in the Stable, the Servants Gadding abroad after their <hi>own Invention,</hi> all their Mony ſpent that he cannot buy any more, and therefore muſt <hi>foot it</hi> about his own occaſions, and ſhe will not ſet her hand to do the leaſt chair in the Houſe, till ſhe hath had a <hi>Fortnights reſt</hi> after her Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling; only go a Viſiting, Chat with her Goſſips, and complain of the unſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceableneſs
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:109001:40"/> of her Husband throughout the whole Journey. The poor Man he ſettles to work, endeavours to ſet all things to rights, takes a great deal of pains; and if any thing is in fault, he's hit <hi>in the Teeth</hi> with it; but if all things be well and in order, that muſt be imputed to her <hi>good management.</hi> In fine, ſhe is ſo taken with her Country-Journey, that ſhe is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to be <hi>Travelling</hi> once a Year, what ever comes on't, and he ſhall be at the Charge of it. Thus his <hi>Expences</hi> increaſe with his Years, he is afflicted with the <hi>Wracking Gout,</hi> and (which is a worſe Diſtemper) a <hi>Froward Woman,</hi> that makes the ſmall Remainder of his days, comfortleſs; for ſhe will <hi>Rule the Roaſt,</hi> muſt have her Will in all things, will be Miſtreſs and <hi>Govern,</hi> whilſt he ſtands only for a <hi>Cipher</hi> at Home, and at length thro Grief and Diſcontent, becomes a meer Skeleton, and Languiſheth away to nothing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="comment">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:109001:41"/>
               <head>The Ninth COMFORT. Old Age Inſulted over.</head>
               <p>WHen a Man hath once thrown him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into the Net, or rather <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of a Family, and taken a brisk Wife, then the <hi>Comforts of Marriage</hi> daily flow in upon him: This Wife you muſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand is a Haughty, Proud Spirited Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and would fain <hi>Domineer</hi> over her Husband; but he being a Prudent Man, manages his Affairs with ſuch Diſcretion, that ſhe, to her great Grief finds, ſhe ſhall never get the <hi>upper hand.</hi> Thus for a time he is Head of the Family, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns his Wife and Children with Credit and reputation; he is <hi>happy</hi> in a <hi>nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Iſſue</hi> of both Sexes; hath Educated them all very well, and Match'd them to good Fortunes; but mark what follows, when all this is done, being <hi>full of years,</hi> the <hi>Infirmities</hi> of Old-age at laſt ſeiſe him, and he is Fettred to his Chamber, by ſome Tedious and Chronical Diſtemper, ſo that he is not able to <hi>move</hi> or <hi>ſtir out</hi> of his Chair. Now the Domeſtick War begins <hi>de novo;</hi> the Wife will <hi>do nothing</hi> but
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:109001:41"/> what ſhe <hi>pleaſeth,</hi> tho ſhe was formerly kept under Hatches; the poor man is now her Priſoner, and at her Mercy; the Wife grows <hi>Surly</hi> and <hi>Sawcy,</hi> the Children Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterleſs, the Servants <hi>Unruly;</hi> and if the Husband attempts to Correct them, ſhe is ready to fly in his face for it. Seeing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf thus Abuſed by <hi>his Wife,</hi> Diſobeyed by his <hi>Children,</hi> and ſlighted by his <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> he takes it very much to heart: But that which <hi>Afflicts</hi> him moſt is the <hi>Extravagancy</hi> of his eldeſt Son and Heir, Bolſtred up by his Mother, only to break the old Man's Heart, and make him end his Life Miſerably. If he thinks of a Will, that he ſhall not be <hi>permitted to do,</hi> for fear he ſhould bequeath ſomewhat to his Poor Relations, or be too Laviſh in Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Legacies: Now the old Gentleman is Left in the Cold alone, unregarded, whilſt ſhe <hi>Goſſips about</hi> in the Pariſh, and declares the Curriſh Uſage of her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; had I not been (ſaith ſhe) a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of a <hi>matchleſs Patience,</hi> I could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have lived with him half this time: but this is not all; for when ſhe comes home ſhe <hi>throws it in his diſh</hi> frequently, and tells him now upbraidingly, that God Rewards him for it. The Good Man is
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:109001:42"/> reſolved to <hi>Admoniſh</hi> her and her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren fairly, to ſee whether that will work <hi>any Good</hi> upon her, and to that end calls them before him: My Dear! you are the only perſon that I ever Loved, and yet give me leave to tell you that I am not pleaſed with <hi>your Carriage</hi> in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Particulars: You know I am Maſter of the Houſe, and will be as long as I live (but, faith, Old Gentleman you are miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, quoth the <hi>good Wife</hi> ſoftly and ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly,) tho I am not uſed like one at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: You know farther how I have ever Cheriſhed you, as the <hi>Beloved Wife</hi> of my Boſom, and kept you as tender as the Apple of my eye, but neither you nor my Children have behaved your ſelves as you ought to do. What would you have done? I trow, ſaith ſhe, you are too well uſed, you do not know when you are well; there is nothing we can do to pleaſe you. Would you have us ſtand <hi>demurely</hi> before you with our fingers in our mouths? Not ſo neither, I do not deſerve this <hi>Taunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Language</hi> at your hands. Then he turns to his eldeſt Son: Son, (ſaith he) I have made ſome Obſervations of <hi>your Behaviour,</hi> with which I am very much Diſſatisfied. You are my Eldeſt Son and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:109001:42"/> Heir 'tis true; but I ſee you <hi>Laviſh away</hi> my Eſtate Profuſely, with Profligate and Debauch'd Company: I have been a good Father, have <hi>Improved your Eſtate,</hi> and ſhall leave you a Plentiful Revenue, if you be Obedient and Dutiful, but otherwiſe, I ſwear by all that is good and Sacred, you ſhall <hi>never enjoy</hi> my Eſtate. What would you have him to do? ſaith ſhe, one ſhall have enough to do to pleaſe you: Do you want for any thing? What would you be at I wonder? I never ſaw the Peer of you, I vow to God; you are neither pleaſed full, nor faſting. Pray Woman hold you your Tongue, and do not uphold him againſt me, tho it hath been ever <hi>your way</hi> to do ſo. This done, the Mother and her Son lay <hi>their Heads</hi> together, and reſolve to give out, that the Old Man is Craz'd, grown a Child again, and make the World believe he is Senſeleſs: if any one comes to ſpeak with him, and asks the Good Lady for the Good Man; ſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently Anſwers, Alas, <hi>Poor Gentleman!</hi> he is faſt enough in God Almighty's Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon; and how came that to paſs, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam? God knows, Sir, for I do not, he is grown a <hi>Dotard,</hi> I am ſure I have no comfort or help of him, God help me,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:109001:43"/> and grant me Patience to undergoe my Afflictions. Truly, Madam, I am hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſorry for it. Thus is the Old Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman <hi>Concealed</hi> from the World, and Confined to his Chamber, ſo that he <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Redreſs</hi> or help himſelf, nor unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the World of the <hi>wrong done him.</hi> This he muſt needs undergo with a great deal of Grief and inward Regret: but ſince he finds no other Remedy, he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to bear it patiently. For my part, I look upon this to be as great a <hi>Torment</hi> as can be upon Earth, for a man to be well <hi>ſtricken in years,</hi> Diſeaſed and Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with a Painful Diſtemper, <hi>Sequeſtred</hi> from all Friends and Relations, debarred of all Company, but ſuch as rather <hi>add to,</hi> than <hi>diminiſh</hi> his Sorrow. Thus he Lingers away in Grief, Pines with Pain, Languiſheth with Sorrow, lives Wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly, but I hope dies Happily; tho my Prayers ſhall be, that Fortune would bring her to ſome ſhameful End, that occaſion'd it, and ſo Farewel, thou worſt of Women!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="comment">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:109001:43"/>
               <head>The Tenth COMFORT. The Fool Rewarded.</head>
               <p>HE that is once decoy'd into the <hi>Net of Matrimony,</hi> muſt bear with his Misfortune as well as he can; for 'tis a hard thing for him to <hi>get out</hi> of the Nooz, when he is once faſtned, as will appear by this enſuing Diſcourſe. Our Married Man here, that is to taſte of the <hi>Tenth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of Marriage</hi> (much good do his heart with it) is but a Puny, Diminutive, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptive Animal, neither gifted with <hi>Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons</hi> nor <hi>Activity</hi> to pleaſe a Wife; and ſhe, after an Eſſay made of his Ability, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains to her Mother, that ſhe cannot love him, he is ſo Lean and Meager, that it is as good lying with a parcel of <hi>Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s <hi>Tools,</hi> as with him, his skin is ſo lanck, and his bones ſo ſharp and extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that when he toucheth her in Bed, he <hi>pricks her</hi> like ſo many Needles, tho not in the proper place, a life that no poor Woman can bear; ſhe wants due Benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and requires <hi>more Milk</hi> than he can give her, and therefore is reſolved to Lap elſewhere. Now the Solace of Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:109001:44"/> begins to appear, <hi>Tantalus</hi>-like, ſhe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> up to the Chin in Water, and can neithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>drink,</hi> nor <hi>eat</hi> thoſe <hi>Apples</hi> that ly <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bing</hi> at her Mouth; a ſad condition for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Hungry and Thirſty Soul: Abroad ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> roams, picks up the firſt <hi>Stallion</hi> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> comes to Hand, and enjoys him as ofte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as ſhe has opportunity. <hi>Stolen Waters ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſweet,</hi> they ſay, and it appears ſo by thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gentlewoman; but the Miſchief on't i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that by ill conduct of Affairs, her Hus<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>band diſcovers her Amorous Intriegue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſpoils her Gaming, and corrects her ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verely for her Impudence; inſomuch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that ſhe <hi>deſerts him,</hi> and goes to he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Friends, Complaining with feigned tear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of his Harſh Uſage to her, and ſhews th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Marks of his ſeverity to her Relations<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who pity her, and curſe him. This i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an excellent Comfort of Matrimony. Thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pleaſure ſalutes him in the very Infancy of his Wedded Condition, and will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly continue to the end. Howeve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Fond Fop, being deprived of his Wife, bemoans her abſence every night in his Widdow'd Sheets, and is at a great loſs for a Bed-fellow: He cannot endure this Life long, and therefore the poor Cornuto muſt ſend for her again; finding him in
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:109001:44"/> this Loving Pickle, Poor thing! the <hi>Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi> of her Affection <hi>wamble</hi> not after a Husband (having been all this while ſtew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the <hi>warm Embraces</hi> of her Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant) and procures her Mother to give out, that ſhe hath been all this while un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her Tutelage; then having an Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to meet with her Husband, Rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles him ſoundly for his <hi>Baſeneſs</hi> toward her Daughter, telling him, that her <hi>Poor Child</hi> was forced to <hi>run away</hi> from him, becauſe ſhe went in danger of her Life all the time ſhe co-habited with him: I had rather, ſaith ſhe, by half, that you would <hi>turn her Home</hi> to me, and part good Friends, than to <hi>abuſe her</hi> ſo as you do; and withal take notice that your Behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to the Poor Girl is enough to make her do what ſhe never thought of, and make your <hi>Headake</hi> in ſpite of your Teeth, take that from me, Sir, ſince you are as you are. Being thus Lectured by the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he ſeems to be <hi>very ſorrowful,</hi> and hath a Months mind to the Daughter; nothing will ſerve him, but he muſt have her again, and has her <hi>de bene eſſe,</hi> upon promiſe of Reformation. Overjoy'd with the <hi>repurchaſe</hi> of his Wife, he grows kind even to Wonder, hops about with her
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:109001:45"/> from place to place, till his Money is all hop'd from him, and then returns home with an <hi>empty Pocket,</hi> but a <hi>heavy Heart,</hi> God knows. Or elſe, if this Wheedle does not take, a Divorce is endeavour'd on both ſides to be procured, but for want of <hi>ſufficient Cauſe</hi> of Separation, or by reaſon of a conſiderable Flaw in the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, the Judge <hi>condemns</hi> them to live according to their <hi>Marriage Vow,</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes a ſmart Fine upon them for their Folly; ſo that the Caſe is worſe and worſe, they are both <hi>doom'd</hi> to a Loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Bed, and a Life which an <hi>Ideot</hi> hath ſenſe enough to avoid, rather than be <hi>ſo tormented,</hi> and expoſe themſelves Ludi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crouſly to the Cenſure of the whole World. Now if it falls out, that there is <hi>ſufficient Cauſe</hi> for a Divorce, their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery is not at all abated; for they muſt never Marry while they live; and if they are not ſo Continent, as to forbear <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nereal Divertiſements,</hi> they muſt e'en run the riſque of a Swinging Clap, and the loſs of Reputation; ſo that by this means they are caught, and faſter in the Net than ever; and if they are of a Noble Family, Rich in Lands and Poſſeſſions, then their <hi>Names are loſt</hi> for want of an
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:109001:45"/> Heir, and they go out of the World with an <hi>ill ſtench,</hi> their Reputation being rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten before their Duſt, and their memory is <hi>more nauſeous</hi> than their Bones in the Grave. He is ſorely troubled at the Bad Report of his Wife, and can go into no Company, but her <hi>miſdeeds</hi> are diſplay'd before him, to his Grief, and her own Shame, an Invenom'd Tongue making a deep and incurable Wound; thus he ſees himſelf the <hi>May-Game</hi> and <hi>Sport</hi> of every Flouting Fellow, and ſilently bears all that's thrown at him: every one has a fling at his Jacket, and the Gallants many at his Wife's Placket, who keep her under his very Noſe, to the grief of his Heart, he pacing about the Town <hi>Acteon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niz'd,</hi> and admir'd by the Boys and Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, a <hi>Torment ſufficient,</hi> I confeſs, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſe a wiſer Head; but no matter, it is no more than he deſerves, and all ſuch <hi>contented Cuckolds:</hi> Let him live as long, and as well as he can, I'll not envy his Happineſs, and when ever he Dyes, I hope I ſhall die in a better, tho not ſo contented a Condition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="comment">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:109001:46"/>
               <head>The Eleventh COMFORT. The Town-Fop with Fleſh in his Pot.</head>
               <p>WHen a brave young Gentleman is at his own <hi>freedom,</hi> and has the World in a ſtring, he may ſteer his own Courſe without care or controle. This our Gallant here, we intend to mention, has a good Eſtate, keeps high Company, Careſſes Handſome Ladies, gives himſelf over to all manner of Pleaſure, is his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's <hi>only Son</hi> and <hi>Joy.</hi> At length this Spark meets with a Young, Comely, Brisk, Sanguine Complexioned Lady, who can never long withſtand a Suit <hi>well managed</hi> with Judgment, and <hi>well-tim'd</hi> with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, (tho every Woman of what Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion ſoever will permit a Man to ſcrew himſelf into her Conſtitution, if ſhe likes him) he hath made many and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Addreſſes to her, laid cloſe Siege to her Chaſtity, ſo that the poor thing is able to hold out no longer, but muſt yield up the Fort, grants his requeſt, and expoſeth her ſelf to his rooſe Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:109001:46"/>
               <p>But the worſt is to come, this is not all; the little <hi>viripotent Youngling</hi> of fifteen is Prolific, and proves with Child, for which there can be no other Remedy than <hi>Concealment,</hi> and as good luck would have it, the Mother had been <hi>in the Oven before,</hi> and underſtood well enough how to make the beſt of a <hi>bad Market,</hi> for the poor Girl knows not ſhe is with Child, tho the Mother does, and ſhe has not long to reckon; ſhe <hi>pukes</hi> every Morning, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſtrange Grimaces, and complains that her ſtomach is <hi>untoward,</hi> and out of order: Well! without all Queſtion, ſaith the Mother, you are with Child; now mind what I am going to ſay to you; as for your Gallant I have forbidden him my Houſe for ever, he being <hi>too mean</hi> a match for you; be ſure, Huſſy, you never open your lips of this <hi>unlucky Job</hi> (which came by Jobbing) to any Chriſtian Soul, and obſerve punctually what I ſhall ſay to you. Did you never take notice of the young Eſquire that comes here ſometimes? yes, Madam, ſaith ſhe; well, take ſpecial notice of him next time, and he has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to be here to Morrow: Behave your ſelf diſcreetly, and ſhow him a Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Countenance: and when you ſpy me
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:109001:47"/> a talking with the reſt of the Company, dart a favourable, <hi>faſcinating Glance</hi> upon him, caſt a ſheeps eye at him, do you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand me, Girl? yes, Madam; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve my directions: if he will keep you in diſcourſe, anſwer him <hi>Modeſtly,</hi> if he proffers you Marriage, return him thanks innocently, but withal give him to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that you <hi>know-not what it is,</hi> nor do you deſire to learn: If he offers you a preſent either of Gold or Silver, be ſure you refuſe it harmleſly; but if it be with a Jewel, Diamond, or Ring; do as Maids uſe to do, deny it modeſtly at firſt, <hi>ſay nay,</hi> and then <hi>take it.</hi> When he takes his leave of you ask him mildly, when you ſhall ſee him again? This Noble Blade is but an <hi>Inch</hi> of <hi>this ſide</hi> of a <hi>Natural,</hi> has a vaſt Eſtate, but a meer Town-Fop, whom the Mother will, if poſſible, work upon to <hi>Marry her Daughter,</hi> ſo that he is in great danger of being caught in the Net, and finely Bubled. Well! he repeats his Viſits, as cloſe as he can one upon the neck of the other: is very well received, ſplendidly Treated, and after dinner with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draws with the young Lady, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements her apart from the Company, takes her by the hand, and thus (like a
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:109001:47"/> fool as he is) accoſts her. Madam, I wiſh with all my Soul, that you <hi>knew</hi> but the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>houghts</hi> of my heart. Alas! Sir, that's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpoſſible, unleſs you diſcover them; I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ope you think of <hi>no harm.</hi> Upon my Faith, not I, Madam, nor of any thing but what I would willingly have you know, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd that without my telling it. Truly Sir, ſaith ſhe, and Uſhers her diſcourſe with a charming Smile: I cannot Divine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd therefore 'tis impoſſible for me to <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand you.</hi> If I thought, Madam, you would not be diſpleaſed, I would faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ully diſcover them. Sir, replies the Young Lady, you have your <hi>freedom</hi> to ſay what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou pleaſe; for I have ſo good an opinion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f you, that I preſume you can ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hing but what is <hi>Commendable</hi> and <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>il.</hi> Madam, ſaith he, I am a Perſon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt confeſs, unworthy to Kiſs your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ands, and dare not preſume to <hi>marry you</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eing a Lady adorn'd with all Natures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erfection: but if you pleaſe to do me that Honour, (expect no Ceremony from me, Madam) I dare boaſt from my Heart, that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ould <hi>love you</hi> with all my Soul, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o man can <hi>love you better,</hi> nor <hi>ſerve you</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith that ſubmiſſion and affection that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an and will, for I reſolve never to forſake
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:109001:48"/> you, let what will befall me, and I ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> tender of your Reputation, as my own. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> return you thanks, Sir, ſaith ſhe, but I be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeech you, ceaſe <hi>your Diſcourſe,</hi> do not har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon that ſtring any longer; for I know not what it means, nor will I learn, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> flat and Categorical; This Diſcour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> would offend my Mother, if it ſhould read<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> her ear. Faith, Madam, your Mother <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a very good Woman; but, if you pleaſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your Mother ſhall know nothing of it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I will be wholly directed by <hi>your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</hi> Why do you ſay ſo, Sir, I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent it would not be for your Good, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would your <hi>Friends adviſe</hi> you to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ny ſuch thing: Pray Sir forbear this kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Talk; for if my Mother ſhould hear i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I am utterly undone, here the Mother gav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> her a <hi>Nod,</hi> ſeeing them both very earne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in Diſcourſe, for fear ſhe ſhould Miſcarry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and not Act her part well: Then the Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> led Youth claps a Ring in her hand, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> begs of her to <hi>accept it</hi> for his ſake; indeed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sir, I ſhall not; I beſeech you, Madam <hi>wear it</hi> for my ſake; well, Sir, ſaith ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at laſt, ſince it muſt be ſo, it ſhall be ſo and I will wear it upon your accoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Then the Mother comes to him, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tells him, to Morrow, Sir, we deſign t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:109001:48"/> ride a little way out of Town, to take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Freſh Air; at which he rejoyceth; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen the time of <hi>Departure</hi> is come, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſineſs is ſo ordered, that there is never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Horſe in the Company <hi>carries double,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut the young Gentleman's, at which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e is not a little pleaſed; ſo it falls out <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>appily,</hi> that his Miſtreſs is ſet <hi>behind</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im, who hugs the Pummel of her Sadle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>r her own Security, I leave you to judge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hether he likes his Company or no: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e Gentleman is very near the Net; for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>is Journey was only undertaken to <hi>catch</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e Young Widgeon; he keeps cloſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Miſtreſs; and when the Mother ſinds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n opportunity, ſhe enquires of her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r <hi>how ſquares go,</hi> and ſhe tells her all: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rom henceforward, ſaith ſhe, Daughter, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hatever you do, carry your ſelf diſcreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, if he talks of Marrying you, tell him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou muſt acquaint me with it, but withal, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>at he is the only Man in the World you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ve, and that you will never have any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut him. Then they take a Walk in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arden, then he takes her by the hand, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ſays, Fine Lady! take pity of me, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſeech you: Pray, Sir, talk no more on't, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r if you do, I will forſake your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>any: Spare me one word more without
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:109001:49"/> offence, if you would be pleaſed to Crow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me with this Happineſs, I ſhould take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for the <hi>greateſt Honour</hi> that was ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> confer'd upon Mortal. Sir, ſaith ſhe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> muſt be <hi>propoſed</hi> to my Relations, or el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I can <hi>ſay nothing</hi> to't: If I thought the would approve of it, I would propoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> my ſelf; for God's ſake, ſaith the cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ning Gipſie, have a care, that you do n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſay a word of my propoſing any ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thing, for I ſhould die through ſhame, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> any ſuch thing ſhould be ſaid of me; n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I, upon my Faith, Madam; and then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> way he goes to the Mother, and diſcou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſes the buſineſs ſo reſpectively, that it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> concluded, and they make up the Mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> immediately; the <hi>ſooner,</hi> the <hi>better,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> things conſidered, for <hi>Hans in Kelda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſake: Now the Poor Gentleman is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Net, and <hi>no body</hi> as yet knows of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but at laſt it comes to the Ears of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, who are <hi>grieved</hi> at the very hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> knowing it to be too inferiour a Mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for their Son: thus they are <hi>Wedded</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>haſte,</hi> and may <hi>repent</hi> at <hi>leiſure;</hi> he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Married without Licence, unaskt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Church, without any Ceremony; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> way in the World, ſo that the buſineſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> once over. Well, night draws on, the Moth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:109001:49"/> takes her Daughter to task, and inſtils ſome of her good, Motherly <hi>Inſtructions</hi> into her, relating to her <hi>Carriage</hi> with her Husband that Night: ſhe charges her to put him <hi>to it</hi> as a Virgin ought to do; and farther, that as ſoon as he entred the Premiſes, with ſome feigned Reluctancy on her part, ſhe muſt fall into a <hi>fainting ſhriek,</hi> as if ſhe had fallen into a cold wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in a hot fit. Thus ſhe Tutors her Daughter to <hi>deceive</hi> the Young Fop. All things hitherto are very well, but mark what follows, there is a <hi>curſed ſting</hi> in the Tail; for within two or three Months, the Young Bride <hi>groans,</hi> and <hi>falls all to pieces;</hi> it could be no longer hid, a Young Babe peeps into the World, and that ſpoils all. Now all the Joy is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into Sorrow, and he knows not what to do with himſelf. He is quite at a loſs: If he turns her away, the whole World will be acquainted with it, and he cannot Marry again, and for her part ſhe will take care of one. 'Tis an ill Hen that can't ſcrape for one Chicken. If he keeps her and co-habits with her, ſhe will never care a Pin for him, nor he for her, there will be no Love loſt of either ſide, I'll be bold to ſay. Well! <hi>All is well
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:109001:50"/> that ends well,</hi> ſaith the good old Adage, and ſo ſay I too; but from ſuch <hi>Comfort</hi> in the Cloſe, from ſuch an End as this, Good Lord deliver me!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="comment">
               <head>The Twelfth COMFORT. The Domineering Wife, and Contented Lap-Dog.</head>
               <p>AND a ſweet one 'tis too, if you knew all. Our Youngſter in this Caſe is one hath beat about the Net ſo long, that at laſt he hath found a hole to creep in at; and to be ſure hath verified the Adage, <hi>faſt bind, faſt find,</hi> he has ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an Indiſſolluble <hi>Knot,</hi> but here is his <hi>Comfort</hi> ſtill, that he hath Married ſuch a <hi>Non pareille,</hi> ſuch a matchleſs Wom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for <hi>Morality, Goodneſs,</hi> and <hi>Vertue,</hi> that ſhe is not to be <hi>Parallel'd</hi> in the <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe:</hi> He admires her <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> extols her <hi>Education,</hi> commends her <hi>Deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> dotes upon her <hi>Face,</hi> is ſo Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated with the Diſtinction of her <hi>Sex,</hi> that he is Raviſh'd with his Choice, and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:109001:50"/> boaſts of his Prudent election; he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to let looſe the Reins of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and permit her to bear the Sway; nothing ſhall be done, but what has firſt the Stamp of her <hi>Approbation:</hi> She is his All, and He her Nothing, nay, you will find at laſt, that ſhe values him little or nothing: He is as <hi>Tame</hi> as a Man, reduc'd by Phlebotomy to a weakly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and made up of nothing but Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. There's my Man (if he hath not forfeited his <hi>Manhood</hi>) as good a Husband <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ever laid Leg over Woman. If His King and Country raiſe an Army to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe a <hi>Foreign Invaſion,</hi> he ſhall not ſtir <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Foot, unleſs ſhe be in the Humour to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ermit him, he ſhall not go to the Wars; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or his Wife is too tender of him to let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im be ſo long out of her ſight; Hang <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he ſhall not March, leſt he returns <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith Grinning or Cripled Honour. Come, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome, Sweet Heart! ſaith ſhe, 'tis good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eeping in a whole Skin; you never was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t out for <hi>Martial Enterprizes;</hi> your Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> is too young and tender to be expoſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Hazard</hi> and <hi>Hardſhip</hi> of <hi>Ruffling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ar:</hi> Let others purchaſe <hi>Renown,</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncy it, at never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o dear a Rate, you ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>joy your ſelf at Home in Peace and Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſs.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:109001:51"/> Thus is the fond Fop abſolutely Governed by his Wife, ſhe has him faſt, and will not loſe an Inch of her hold If ſhe has a mind to Juncket and Sport with her Gallant, he muſt to Bed, and <hi>then the Gooſe is laid to the Fire.</hi> Some times ſhe puts him in mind of urgent Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, and then he muſt <hi>riſe at Midnigh</hi> to diſpatch it; or elſe ſhe expoſes him to a Journey, that ſhe may have the bette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Opportunity</hi> to enjoy her Friend; or h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt riſe all Hours in the Night to fet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> her a <hi>Doctor</hi> to cure the <hi>Stich</hi> or <hi>Pain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Side,</hi> and expoſe himſelf to the injur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Weather, when in the <hi>interim</hi> ſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admits her Gallant, who is ſo bold as t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Scale the Walls, creep in at the Window and a thouſand ſuch little <hi>Love-Toys, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> accompliſh</hi> his Deſign and Deſire. Som<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> times it falls out that her Friend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Planted himſelf behind the Hangings, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> her <hi>miſchievous</hi> little <hi>Lap-dog</hi> ſmells hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> out, and ſhe tells her Husband, they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rats and Mice that he Barks at, and pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſwades him 'tis the poor <hi>Cur</hi>'s <hi>Cuſtom</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> do ſo; but at laſt ſhe frightens him awa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with, Out you little <hi>Foiſting Cur,</hi> what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Noiſe is here with you? and then he <hi>ſnea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> away</hi> like a dog that has burnt his Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:109001:51"/> She makes him dandle the Child to ſleep, and ſing a <hi>Nocturnal Lullaby</hi> to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Babe, while he like an Innocent Fool does it without <hi>Murmuring:</hi> ſhe makes him carry the Diſtaff or Spindle, whilſt ſhe is cutting out more work for him: ſhe ſpins a fair Thread at laſt, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to his coſt finds that, <hi>he hath brought his Hogs to a fair Market.</hi> In ſhort, like a Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>el he is made to fetch and carry, when, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd what ſhe pleaſes; the poor Fop never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>njoys a minutes reſt or content, runs thro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> World of Sorrow and Tribulation, and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et him, unpitied for me; for he ſeems to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e created to no other End. He has brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n old Houſe over his Head, which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntly until'd, if he ſpeaks but one word <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> contradict her: ſhe has got the upper Hand of him, and 'tis now too late to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> her: had he taken her down in her Wedding-ſhoes, there might have been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>opes of doing ſome good with her; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is in vain, nay impoſſible to work upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er now.</p>
               <p>Thus he grows Aged through <hi>Care, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rief</hi> and <hi>Vexation,</hi> is ſlighted by his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame, like an old <hi>Faulkner,</hi> or to ſpeak <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore properly, like an Old Wife (the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orſt of Creatures,) good for nothing.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:109001:52"/> His (or rather-her) <hi>Domeſtick Affairs,</hi> he muſt not intermeddle with: ſhe is the <hi>Domina fac totum;</hi> and if any of he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Daughters be Marriageable, ſhe diſpoſeth of them to whom ſhe pleaſeth, withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Conſent or Approbation: If they are well Matcht, well and good: if ill he dares not find fault with it, much leſs upbraid her for it. She <hi>plays the Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> man</hi> exactly, and will have her Will in every thing, right or wrong, there is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gainſaying, unleſs he has a mind to make the Houſe too hot to hold him. Now Appeal to all <hi>Rational Men,</hi> what greate Torment can there be to a Man that ſuch a Ruling Houſwiſe? what greate Plague to a Husband than ſuch a <hi>Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> neering</hi> Wife? O the unutterable com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fort of ſuch an eaſie, pleaſant Life, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the good Woman takes all the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>the upon her own Shoulders, Manages a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Affairs at home and abroad, and he no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo much as concerned with any, live happily and free from the <hi>Cares</hi> and <hi>Tur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> moils</hi> of a Wedded Life, Dies with Grie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Shame, to ſee himſelf ſo Conquer by his Wife, and ſo ſneaks out of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> World, quite weary of it, without pit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or compaſſion: There let him reſt quie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:109001:52"/> in his <hi>Grave,</hi> that never did ſo in his Life-time, without <hi>Epitaph</hi> or <hi>Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> but that everlaſting one of his Folly, that he left behind him to Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="comment">
               <head>The Thirteenth COMFORT. The Wedded Widdower, and Single Wife.</head>
               <p>THis Gentleman we are to treat of here, is of a quite different Temper from the laſt, who will not be Rul'd by his Wife, but is of a <hi>Noble, Martial Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> and runs in purſuit of <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Fame.</hi> He is reſolved to venture his Life and Fortune in his Princes Service be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond-Sea, and in order thereunto firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints his Wife with his unſhaken Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution; ſhe Embraces and Careſſes him with Tears, in her Eyes: Alas! my dear, ſaith ſhe, can you have the heart to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake me and the Pledges of our Love, theſe ſweet Babes? will you now deſert me, and leave me and my Children to the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:109001:53"/> wide World, Comfortleſs and Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, when we have lived ſo contentedly, as Man and Wife, for ſome years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? My Dear! ſaith he, I muſt go, my Honour lies at <hi>ſtake,</hi> which is dearer than Life and all in the World beſides. I muſt obey my King, or forfeit my <hi>Loyalty,</hi> and the Eſtate that I hold of his Majeſty by <hi>Tenure</hi> to ſerve him in his Wars; but in Grace of God I hope to ſee you ſuddenly, if he pleaſe to continue my Life and Health, and he is beſt able to provide for you. Thus he takes leave of his Wife with a heavy heart, and ſhe is as big with ſeeming ſorrow at <hi>their parting;</hi> recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending her, and his Children to the <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Tuition</hi> of his Friends. Aſſoon as he arrives at the Camp, he being an active, brave Soul, cannot reſt without ſome attempt to <hi>ſignalize his Valour,</hi> and attacques the Enemy with ſo brisk an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault, that he clears all before him, ſo the Diſpute continues hot on both ſides a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable time, but at laſt, <hi>ſtimulated</hi> by Honour and Glory, preſſes too far into the Body of the Enemy, and the Poor Gentleman has the misfortune to be taken Priſoner, and there is kept three or four Years, before he can procure an Exchange
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:109001:53"/> or Ranſom to obtain his Liberty. His Lady is very <hi>Inquiſitive</hi> after his Welfare, and at laſt receives ſome ſlight and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Information of his Death, which ſhe ſeems to take very Grievouſly, and falls into an exceſs of <hi>Sorrow;</hi> but certainly Women were not Created only to weep; beſides inordinate Grief is prohibited and ſinful. God be thanked, in a very ſhort time this grief is over, and ſhe is married to another. The <hi>entire Affection</hi> ſhe had for her former Husband and his Iſſue is quite forgot and loſt; all her fond Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reffes and Embraces before, and at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, are buried with him (as ſhe thinks) in Oblivion, without hopes of a Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; ſhe ſhews more love to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond than ſhe did to her firſt Husband; but that <hi>fickle Baggage</hi> Fortune will have it ſo, that her Husband at length is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed, returns Home, tho much decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and broken by the ſeverity of his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, and the hard uſage he receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Enemy. No ſooner arrived, but he makes diligent <hi>Inquiſition</hi> after his Wife and Children, and the thoughts of their miſcarriage, did certainly much ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate the affliction and grief of his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity. At laſt he underſtands the diſmal
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:109001:54"/> and unwelcome news of her Second Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage: now judge you what a Confuſion he is in at this <hi>ſtabbing</hi> Relation. The anguiſh of <hi>Priam</hi> King of <hi>Troy,</hi> when he was acquainted with the Death of <hi>Hector,</hi> was not certainly comparable to his; at laſt he comes Home, and is fully inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of all the particulars. What a Diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction he now is in may poſſibly be faintly imagined, but never fully expreſt; what Courſe to <hi>ſteer,</hi> or how to grapple with this Misfortune, is a <hi>Controverſie</hi> that cannot well be decided. What Revenge can he ſtudy ſuitable to her Crime? what puniſhment doth ſhe not deſerve to have inflicted upon her for <hi>Faithleſſneſs?</hi> As he is a Man of Courage and Honour he can never be ſo <hi>Puny-ſpirited</hi> as to put up this Injury unſatisfied, nor can he buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le to ſo tame and unmanly a <hi>Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> as to re-admit her into his Bed, tho her Husband ſhould diſpence with it. On the other ſide, he who Married her laſt muſt needs be very much diſturbed at this unlucky Buſineſs, and having been ſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated with her, muſt hate and forſake her, for Love and Empire never admit of <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivals.</hi> And what a ſad Caſe now is ſhe in by her over-forwardneſs and Creduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty?
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:109001:54"/> ſhe has loſt her Reputation; both her Husbands and her own Honour, hath bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried all her Modeſty in the Grave of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy, and expoſed her ſelf to the <hi>Virulent</hi> Tongues of carping <hi>Momi;</hi> her Children will be afflicted and diſturbed at the Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune of the Mother, the vexation of the Father, and conſequently at the Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity of both their Parents.</p>
               <p>Thus they two, who might have lived comfortably all their days, by this unlucky accident, are like to live miſerably, to whom length of days, the greateſt Happineſs on Earth, will <hi>prove</hi> their greateſt Miſery. Marry they muſt not, cannot, dare not: This is one of the deſireable Comforts of Matrimony: One of the Enjoyments of a Wedded Life: One of the Pleaſures of a Coupled Condition. They muſt live aſunder withour hopes of a <hi>re-union,</hi> he muſt die a Wedded Widdower, and ſhe a ſingle Wife, an unhappy Myſtery to both, and an unfortunate, tho unheard of Paradox.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="comment">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:109001:55"/>
               <head>The Fourteenth COMFORT. The Diſconſolate Widower juſtly puniſh'd.</head>
               <p>HE that is ſenfible of this Comfort is one, who hath taken ſuch pains to find a paſſage into the Net, that he is got in and enſnared by a young, beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and well tempered Woman; and they enjoy their Delights and Pleaſures without <hi>Contention</hi> or <hi>Diſturbance;</hi> a happy life indeed, and ſuch as might make a Man thirſt after the <hi>Cup</hi> of <hi>Matrimony.</hi> They <hi>Careſs</hi> one another <hi>inceſſantly,</hi> like two <hi>Turtles,</hi> for they are two in one united; and if the one is in the leaſt Diſcompos'd, the other <hi>Sympathiſeth</hi> in the pain and Affliction; but theſe are <hi>Halcyon Days,</hi> too ſerene and calm to laſt long; for the Wife dies ſuddenly, and puts a Period to all their Amours and Happy Enjoyments. The Young Man grows very Diſconſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, bewails Night and Day the Irrepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Loſs of his Wife; ſometimes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of Death, and other times of the <hi>Capriciouſneſs</hi> of <hi>Verſatile</hi> Fortune, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's <hi>Whirlegig,</hi> that is always turning,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:109001:55"/> and never fixed or ſetled. Thus for ſome time he lives in Miſery, ſhuns all Society, abandons all Comfort, ruminating upon his Misfortune, the Deprivation of ſo good and kind a Comfort: He dreams of her <hi>continually,</hi> thinks of her without <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,</hi> and loves her Memory. But it is as true, as old a ſaying, <hi>nullum violentum eſt perpetuum: Sorrows are ſhort, that are ſharp and violent.</hi> But after all, this our young Gentleman tho he hath been once catcht in the <hi>Net,</hi> and freed, muſt be ſo Foppiſh as to venture a ſecond time, and is baited into it again, to his great Grief and Diſcontent: by a Widdow, who is a Perſon of a quite contrary Humour to his former Wife, of a middle Age: Firſt ſhe carries her ſelf very demurely with tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Diſcretion; but at length, when ſhe hath ſufficiently pried into his Temper, and throughly underſtands his Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then ſhe begins to ſhew her Teeth, and play upon his <hi>ſweet Diſpeſition</hi> (a Fault too incident to that Sex) brings him to her bow, and manages him to her beſt advantage, ſhe ſtudying nothing but her own, not his Satisfaction: And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly there are no ſuch <hi>Vaſſals</hi> in the worſt of Servitude, who are ſo enſlaved, as ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:109001:56"/> Young Men, when link'd to Widdow'd Women, eſpecially when they are of a Croſs and Sordid Humour; and he that is ſo unfortunate as to be reduced to this <hi>Extremity,</hi> has no other Redreſs, but to pray to God to grant him Patience to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo this <hi>weighty</hi> Affliction; if that won't do, his utmoſt Refuge is to have recourſe to a Silken Halter, and ſo ſtrangle himſelf together with his Miſery. Now ſhe begins to appear in her <hi>Colours;</hi> ſhe grows Jealous of him (the very Bane of a Married Life) and is ſo inſatiable that ſhe is diſſatisfied, if he be but a minute out of her <hi>Embraces,</hi> cannot endure him out of her ſight, and every Woman he caſts an Eye upon, he luſts after. When Widdows meet with young Fleſh, they cheriſh it, becauſe it renews their Strength and Vigour; and there is nothing more Noiſome, or prejudicial to a Young man's Health, than a <hi>Laſcivious, Draining, Old Wife:</hi> Yet I look upon an Old Man to be the greater Bruit of the two, who Smugs and Trims himſelf up with all Artificial Ornaments to make him appear Youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and then Marries a Young Girl: That is a moſt intolerable piece of Vanity, a Foppery neither to be allowed, nor imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated:
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:109001:56"/> His Nauſeous Breath, proceeding from the corruption of <hi>Decayed Lungs,</hi> muſt needs offend beyond Expreſſion; Coughing, Sneezing, Spawling, Groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Spitting (tho not a word of ſpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the right Baſon) muſt needs be very unacceptable to Youth, if not <hi>Odious</hi> and <hi>Loathſome:</hi> But to return to our Young Gentleman, taken in the Net a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time (the greater his Folly) his Wife grows ſo greedy after <hi>Man's Fleſh,</hi> that ſhe could find in her heart to turn <hi>She-Canibal,</hi> and devour it ſhe is ſtark mad with Jealouſie, and if he goes to Church with never ſuch Real, Pious and Devout <hi>Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> ſhe ſuſpects he has ſome <hi>Siniſter</hi> and <hi>Wicked Deſigns.</hi> I am apt to believe, there can be no <hi>Real Love</hi> without ſome ſmack or ſpice of <hi>Jealouſie:</hi> for certainly no Man or Woman would match them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to a Creature, who had no good Quality, or Parts to create an <hi>Inclination</hi> in a ſecond Perſon towards them, that would betray the <hi>Fooliſhneſs</hi> of their <hi>Choice;</hi> but this ſort of Jealouſie, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Suſpicion, occaſions no <hi>Domeſtick Feuds,</hi> or <hi>Houſhold Jarrs,</hi> becauſe it is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an Exceſs of Kindneſs or Affection; but that which creates a groundleſs Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicion
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:109001:57"/> and Diffidence of the <hi>Party belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> and ends in Brawling and Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, muſt needs be the worſt of <hi>Plagues,</hi> and the Curſed Sting and Torment of <hi>Matrimony.</hi> If theſe be the <hi>Comforts</hi> of a Married Life, let me enjoy my Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and Freedom in a ſingle State, and live happily without Diſſatisfaction or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance. I do not in the leaſt blame the <hi>State of Matrimony,</hi> miſtake me not; but the Raſh and Precipitate Election of thoſe Hotſpurs, that run headlong into that Condition without deliberate Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration. <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> the Famous <hi>Greek</hi> Phyſician, hath a ſmart ſaying, and very pertinently Applicable to our young Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, <hi>Vetulam non novi, cur morior?</hi> I never Wedded an old Wife, and why ſhould I die? it had been well for him, if he had laid this Sentence to heart, and matcht himſelf to one of his own youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Temper, then he might have liv'd happily and contentedly, tho here we muſt take our leave of him, gaſping for his laſt Breath in a wretched and deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>able Condition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="comment">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:109001:57"/>
               <head>The Fifteenth COMFORT. The double Cajoal.</head>
               <p>THis is a great and Prodigious <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> a <hi>Comfort</hi> that cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt ſignificantly. Our Married Man here chanceth to meet with a Woman who is much addicted to the ſhaking of her <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow,</hi> as well as of her <hi>Tail,</hi> two good Qualities in a good Wife, and the good Man is like to thrive upon't. This courſe of Life ſhe leads for a conſiderable time undiſturbed, becauſe undiſcover'd, but at length he finds his Eſtate decay by her expenſive <hi>Gaming;</hi> ſuſpects her Fidelity, and is reſolved to watch an opportunity, to diſcover, if poſſible, her <hi>Amorous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues:</hi> And one day, as <hi>Fate</hi> would have it, he enters her Chamber privately, and ſurprizeth her in the <hi>very Action,</hi> or in a very ſuſpicious and wanton poſture. The Husband incenſed with Rage and Fury, cannot contain himſelf any longer within bounds, but flies at her <hi>Gallant</hi> with a deſign to make him <hi>breath out his laſt</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Spot,</hi> but as he is ſtriking at him,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:109001:58"/> his Wife, <hi>kind Soul!</hi> (as it behoves her; for ſhe ought not to ſtand by, and be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Murder,) comes and embraces her Husband; Ah! for Gods ſake, my Dear, have a care that you do not hit an <hi>unlucky Blow,</hi> and be Guilty of Blood-ſhed; whereupon the Blade clears himſelf of his intended Aſſaſſine, and ſhews him a fair pair of Heels; 'twas well he was nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-footed, or elſe he had certainly been ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed to his <hi>Fury;</hi> but <hi>Fear</hi> and <hi>Guilt</hi> have Wings as well as <hi>Love,</hi> and in ſhort he makes his eſcape. The Husband pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues him, but to no purpoſe; for he hath ſecured himſelf by Flight: whereupon he returns like a <hi>Hungry, Rampant Lion</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Chamber, thinking to meet with his Wife, and make her <hi>his Prey;</hi> but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las! the <hi>Bird is flown.</hi> Now what think you is become of this Unfortunate and Diſconſolate Woman? why ſhe is fled to her Relations, and acquaints them with all theſe Paſſages in a <hi>Mournful Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alect,</hi> with ſome ſeeming Regret. At this Relation all the whole Family is in an uproar; ſometimes blaming him for his Severity, but her, moſt of all, for her Impudence and Indiſcretion. The Wife <hi>palliates</hi> the buſineſs to <hi>her Mother,</hi> at the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:109001:58"/> firſt, but upon ſtrict Examination Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth with Sighs and Tears the whole matter (the Mother underſtanding very well how to manage a Cauſe of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, who had her ſelf been guilty of the ſame miſcarriage, tho with more Privacy and Secrecy, without Injury to her Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation by ſo <hi>Palpable</hi> and <hi>Notorious</hi> a <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery</hi>) Well! they meet and conſult how to ſmother the buſineſs, and by Menaces on the one hand, and Intreaties on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand, to reduce the eaſie natur'd Husband to a better Temper, and by all means poſſible, to patch up a <hi>Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and make Peace between them. In order thereunto, firſt they tamper with his Chamber-Maid, a <hi>Procureur d'Amour,</hi> a Procuring Bawd, or Female Pander to her Miſtreſſes Luſt, and they ask her how it is with her Maſter, ſince this unlucky <hi>Diſaſter?</hi> To whom ſhe replies, he is in a very deſperate, diſcontented Condition, hath taken no ſuſtenance at all ſince that Misfortune happ'ned, nor had any Reſt or Sleep to Refreſh him. When he ſate down to Dinner, this Day, he did not ſwallow ſo much as one Morſel, his Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach was too weak to entertain food; then he ſits as Melancholy as one that is
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:109001:59"/> Hypocondriacal; has a gaſtly, wan look, as if <hi>Grief</hi> had drunk up all the colour of his face. Sometimes he wrings his Hands, ſhakes his Head, bites his Fingers ends, takes his Knife, and ſticks it in the Table, and afterward throws it away with great Indignation. Then preſently, on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, ſtarts up and takes a <hi>Promenade</hi> in the Garden, but returns with a diſtracted look, before he hath paſſed thirty Yards; he can neither ſit nor ſtand ſtill one mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute in a place; Night and Day he ſighs, bemoans himſelf, that it would extort pity from a <hi>Barbarian,</hi> to ſee him in this ſad Condition. Well! at length, after ſome time <hi>elapſed,</hi> when they Judged the ſtorm was ſomewhat over, and that he was grown more <hi>cool</hi> and <hi>temperate.</hi> Some of the moſt forward and crafty of that Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Gang of her Friends and Relations attacque the Husband, like the Northern Wind, bluſteringly, and the Tempeſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over, ſtrike Sail, and diſcourſe with as great <hi>Moderation</hi> and <hi>Subtlety,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending his Wife for her <hi>Vertue, Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty,</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> (a pious Devil indeed) and that they have known her for ſeveral Years to live like a Modeſt Wife, with an unſtained <hi>Reputation,</hi> obedient to your
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:109001:59"/> ſelf, reſpective to her Neighbours, and civil to all Perſons of both <hi>Sexes.</hi> Now for you openly to defame her, to the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of her <hi>Honour,</hi> upon ſome imaginary ſurmize, is unkind, and injurious in ſo high a nature, that you can never make her amends: beſides, Sir, let me be plain with you in a buſineſs of ſo great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, ſay, or think what you will, to my own certain knowledge, two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may be cloſely engaged in Diſcourſe together, in a very friendly poſture, and yet not do the thing that you imagine, nor ever ſo much as entertain a thought of ſo Diſloyal and Immodeſt an Action, as to defile their <hi>Husband</hi>'s <hi>Bed.</hi> What he might, like a <hi>bold Ruffian</hi> attempt, I will not here diſpute, that is none of my pretence, but Foreign to the <hi>matter in hand;</hi> yet this I'll confidently aver and maintain againſt all oppoſition, that there is no Man breathing, that your Lady hates like <hi>this Villain,</hi> who hath ſo raſhly brought an old Houſe over her Head; nay, I am ſatisfied in my Conſcience, that ſhe would ſooner ſee him ſuffer the moſt <hi>Ignomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Death</hi> that ever was executed upon the moſt <hi>Notorious Criminal,</hi> than per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him to touch her in an uncivil way.
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:109001:60"/> Let me perſwade you to conſult your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and not thus ruffle and diſcompoſe your ſelf with a meer <hi>Chimaera</hi> or Fancy; the <hi>poor Woman</hi> is ſo ſwell'd with Tears, that ſhe hath ſcarce an Eye to peep out of, wrings her hands, bewails her condition, and laments without intermiſſion, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure you have conceived againſt her; it lies in your power yet to make up the buſineſs, with a <hi>Salvo</hi> to her, and your own Reptutation; for long ſhe cannot continue in this <hi>languiſhing condition,</hi> and I hope you do not thirſt after her blood, that were Inhuman and Unchriſtian. Come, come, Sir, let me tell you, you muſt foget and forgive, if there were (tho I ſee no) cauſe for either, upon your Wife's account: Beſides, do you think, if your Wife were a <hi>Diſſolute Woman,</hi> a Woman of tainted Reputation, that we would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalue our ſelves ſo much, as to keep her Company? No, no, never cheriſh any ſuch thought in you, for that were to ſtab our Fame and Honour, as well as hers: Nay, Sir, I muſt tell you farther, I have been acquainted with her from her Child-hood, and am ſo far from know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing harm by her, that I dare maintain, ſhe has been the <hi>Pattern</hi> of <hi>Vertue</hi> in this
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:109001:60"/> Country. What, ſaith the Husband, will you perſwade me out of my Senſes? I ſaw it with my own eyes. In good Faith, 'tis no ſuch thing, ſay what you will; the Senſes are fallible, for want of a proper <hi>Medium,</hi> or through ſome weakneſs or imperfection in the <hi>Optics.</hi> O Brave Dame! well <hi>Philoſophis'd,</hi> I proteſt: we uſe to ſay, <hi>Seeing is believing;</hi> but in this caſe, it ſeems, a Man muſt not believe his own eyes. Well! the Husband begins to be of a more Sedate and Serene Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and conſiders <hi>with himſelf,</hi> that Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie caſts a Miſt before the ſight, and makes a Man <hi>ſee double,</hi> or very imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly: So now he is reſolved tamely to put up all wrongs, wipe his mouth, and be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent for the future; the Women ſmile to ſee the Buſineſs ſo <hi>well managed,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to bring them together again, and take their leave of him for the preſent. Thus the facil Gentleman is convinced of his Errour, and very much troubled, that ever he entertained ſuch a Thought, and ſo he receives his Wife again, and all things are buried in <hi>their mutual Embraces.</hi> Now what think you will be the Iſſue of all this? ſhe upon this grows Inſolent, and hits him in the Teeth with his Recognition
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:109001:61"/> and Acknowledgement, upbraiding him with the Injury he hath done her. The Gallant and Neighbours muſt be Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a coſtly Collation to put up the buſineſs, and now they may enjoy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves without Controul, her Friend <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> her, and ſhe him, <hi>one good turn,</hi> you know, <hi>deſerves another,</hi> and <hi>Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude</hi> is the <hi>Blackeſt</hi> of Crimes. Thus ſhe is a <hi>Lady Paramount,</hi> conſumes his Eſtate with Gaming, waſtes his Body with grieving him, perſecutes his Soul, till it takes its flight, and ſo at laſt, loaden with Years and Cares, is wafted over in <hi>Charon</hi>'s Ferry, to the <hi>Elyſian</hi> Shades; and there's an end of his Miſery.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="comment">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:109001:61"/>
               <head>The Sixteenth COMFORT. The Poor Man's Comfort.</head>
               <p>NOw we are come into the Teens, and paſt thorow the better half of our <hi>Matrimonial Solaces,</hi> we will diſcourſe a little of this Sixteenth, which is a poor and pitiful Comfort indeed; for here <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nury</hi> and <hi>Pertinacy</hi> are Wedded together, as well as Man and Wife, both of them are Children of the <hi>Mean Mob,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane <hi>Vulgus,</hi> or what you pleaſe to term them, mean in Parentage, as well as in Parts and Purſe, he but of ordinary, and ſhe of no extraordinary Mold, yet in time, after ſome Years Co-habitation and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>operation, they are bleſt with a Nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Company of brats (Chargeable Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings indeed, and fitter for the Pariſh to maintain than this Couple) they Drudge, Moil, Toil, and do all that can as yet be requir'd, but by and by you muſt be roun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Ear with another diſmal Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and you know very well, or at leaſt I will inform you, that it is an old Proverb with the <hi>Phlegmatick Butter-box,</hi> when
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:109001:62"/> any thing is done effectually and to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, they ſay, <hi>'tis perform'd as poor men get Children.</hi> But to proceed, if they prove negligent, the craving Appetite of the Bawling and Pratling Babe will ſoon wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry them into a remembrance of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rental Office, in providing for their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, ſince they were not ſo cautious as to make Proviſion before they engaged themſelves raſhly in that <hi>incumbent Duty.</hi> Thus the Good Man after a hard days Drudgery, having been at it before the Sun appear'd in our Hemiſphere, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued it till he is gone to beſtow his kind influence upon the <hi>Antipodes,</hi> who when tir'd Nature requiring ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment, he ſits at one end of the Houſe like the Image of a <hi>Slovenly Mechanic,</hi> and ſhe like the ſluttiſh <hi>Effigies</hi> of Charity, with one Child at her Breaſt, a ſecond in her Lap, a third upon the Ground, graſping her Knees, and the reſt about them crying for Bread, bawling for Drink, ſcreaming to be undreſt, gaping and yawning to be laid to ſleep: (a charming noiſe, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing harmony no doubt, enough to drive a man out of his wits, for not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo much previous wit, as to conſider it before) thus they have both their hands
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:109001:62"/> and heart full, God help them, he <hi>Rocks</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>Cradle,</hi> and ſhe feeds the hungry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mily, and all little enough to ſatisfie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e grumbling of their <hi>craving Maws.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aving been thus, for ſome Years, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ced with the Comforts of Matrimony, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e begins to find his <hi>Wedded Life</hi> irk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me, which makes him neglect his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>irs, ſlight his Buſineſs, Charges ſtill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>creaſing, and Trade decaying, now he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <hi>taken heart,</hi> and is reſolved for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ture to make uſe of the too common <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ode of theſe times, to turn a <hi>Good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llow,</hi> frequent the Tipling-Houſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore than formerly, and his Shop leſs; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y if his Stock will at any time reach <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he will to Tavern, and there ſing <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d Roſe,</hi> till Night and the Conſtable, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ho Summon all to go to their Reſt and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abitations; then he Reels Home with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mptineſs in his Pocket, Rage in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ooks, and Vexation in his Heart; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd there he meets with a <hi>ſecond Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unter</hi> worſe than the former, from his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ife (a Domeſtick, but ſometimes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tameable Animal) Well <hi>Thomas!</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith ſhe) doſt thou think that I am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le to endure this curſed Life? or can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u imagine, that I muſt be confin'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Home, with a parcel of Children
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:109001:63"/> about my ears <hi>without Bread</hi> and <hi>Drink</hi> to put in their Heads, whilſt you are Revelling abroad Night and day, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong your Sottiſh Companions: I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bear it any longer, but am reſolv'd to go abroad too, and then do you take care and provide for the Children: I'll learn out your Haunts, and <hi>find you out</hi> if you are above ground, ne'r fear it; and and then aſſure your ſelf, I'll Ring you and your Drunken Aſſociates ſuch a peal, as ſhall ſoon break up your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. He being heated with Drink, and naturally a ſurly, ſower Fellow, lays his <hi>brawny Arms</hi> upon her, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects her for her Scolding, inſomuch that ſhe is forced to keep Houſe for a Week or Fortnight, to prevent the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd <hi>black</hi> and <hi>blew Livery</hi> of her Eyes and Face from being diſcovered by the Goſſiping Neighbourhood; he in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terim gets up in the Morning, and away to the Alehouſe to refreſh himſelf, and torment her at Home for her laſt Nights Work. Now he's grown irretriveably loſt, as to his Trade and Family, works very little, and that <hi>more for outward ſhew</hi> than any thing elſe, is grown ſo bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his new Gang of pot Companions, that he has taken reſolution to Rant,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:109001:63"/> Tear and fling the Helve after Hatchet; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut Money he <hi>muſt procure</hi> by one means <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> other, to maintain him in this Debauched Courſe of life, partly by his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wn <hi>Inclination,</hi> and the repeated Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſions of his beloved Friends; then the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouſhold Moveables muſt march off, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd be engaged for the ſupply of his <hi>Extravagant Expences,</hi> till there are no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore to move out of the Cottage. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oor Woman at Home ſeeing all going <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ruine and deſtruction, grows Impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ient at his Miſcarriages, and reſolves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon her <hi>Dernier Effort,</hi> to make her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ords good (as ſhe had formerly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>niſed) ſhe in a Rage flies out, and is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon the <hi>queſt</hi> to <hi>find him</hi> and <hi>his Haunts;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> laſt, by ſome information, or poſſibly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y meer Accident (for Wives are very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cceſsful in conjectures of this Nature, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ven to admiration) ſhe hits on it, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhe dances with this Salutation to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eople at the Bar, <hi>Is my Husband here?</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, in ſuch a Room; away ſhe goes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd aſſoon as ever ſhe enters, finds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem at the heighth of their Mirth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>moaking, Drinking, Singing, Swearing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd what not? but that which exaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erates her moſt, is, a <hi>dirty Doxie</hi> Tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:109001:64"/> among them, as impudent in her Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour as contemptible in her Garb, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> like will to like, Jack <hi>will have his</hi> Gill, <hi>and</hi> Jone <hi>is as good as my Lady.</hi> Impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent at this Baggage, that toucheth he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Copy-hold ſo cloſely, the Hurrican is nigh at hand by <hi>black Clouds</hi> of he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Countenance, and with a Volley of up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiding words, ſuch as Jade, Whore, Bitch, what <hi>dare you keep my Husband Company,</hi> to the Ruine of him and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily? Then follows a Broad-ſide o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pots, Cans, Candleſticks, Pipes (and here the deſtruction of Pipes becomes the Generation of Stoppers) and 100 to one, if in this ſharp Counterſcuffle n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> great Miſchief be done, ſhe certainly gives the Gentlewoman ſome <hi>ſlight Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of her Honeſty, which ſhe certainly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to the Grave. In this confuſed Scene of Rage and Fury, the ſurprize doth a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> baſh the whole Company (but more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly her Husband) inſomuch, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they uſe all poſſible ſmooth Language t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pacifie her Wrath, which with much ado is effected by <hi>diſcharging</hi> the Wenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> privately by the conveyance of ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>back way,</hi> and ſo break up the Company Now he knows not what courſe to ſtee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (for he's ſatisfied he ſhall never enjoy
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:109001:64"/> a quiet minute with her for the future) unleſs it be to <hi>Barbadoes</hi> or <hi>Jamaica</hi> (the uſual Receptacle of Debauched and Crackt Artificers) which he ſoon effects, and ſo at laſt, having ſold all that he hath, <hi>ſells himſelf</hi> too, packs away, and is gone the firſt Wind that ſerves for his turn; leaves his Children as an <hi>inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to the Pariſh,</hi> and his Wife to the <hi>Almes houſe,</hi> if they will be ſo Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, as to do it, conſidering her Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune. Thus you may ſoon gueſs at the iſſue of this <hi>Comfort of Matrimony:</hi> the Wife has left this wide World to beg in, but only the expectancy of a ſingle Pariſh to maintain her: the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band is <hi>tranſported</hi> into another World, where through a ſtream of Exceſs and Intemperance, with the heat of the Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, <hi>ſwims</hi> into a third, in a very litle time, and ſo dies a Slave and Stranger, imperiouſly inſulted over whilſt alive, and when dead, quoited into a hole, without the leaſt Mourning, or indeed ſo much as Chriſtian Burial</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="comment">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:109001:65"/>
               <head>The Seventeenth COMFORT. The fatal Couple.</head>
               <p>AND this will appear to be mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrange and incredible than al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thoſe that preceed, by reaſon of its <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany,</hi> and the fatal conſequences there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Here a Gentleman of good Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Education, but <hi>better Fortune,</hi> who by the conſent of his Parents is diſpoſed of to as <hi>Opulent</hi> a Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and every way correſpondent to him in Youth, Parts and Portion: he Careſſes with hot and frequent Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes of Love; wiſhes that he might grow to her Threſhold, that he might have the more frequent Fruition of her never-enough <hi>admired</hi> Society; ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns anſwer to all his fervent Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, with a moſt becoming and charming Modeſty; ſo that upon the ſtricteſt Obſervations of their mutual Deportment, nothing can be diſcern'd but a Matchleſs Amorous Paſſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them reciprocally. When a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient time is thus ſported away, by making their Amours, the Nuptial Ceremony (after preparations neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:109001:65"/> in Affairs of this Nature) is Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated, (and nothing but Joy and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ſeems to attend their <hi>Cohabitation</hi>) which for continuance of time, delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Viands, luxurious Wines, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all ſorts of other Liquors, Balls, Muſick, Jollity, and other Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions, indeed for plenty of all things, beſides the numerous Train of Invited Gueſts, Servants and Attendants, was <hi>never exceeded;</hi> nay, 'tis yet a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unanſwered, whether ever <hi>equalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed</hi> in this preſent, or ſome preceeding Ages. After the Ceremony of <hi>Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nization</hi> is over, they Love as affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, Live as ſplendidly, as their <hi>Port</hi> can poſſibly bear (and further too, as you will ſpeedily be ſatisfied) in their Country-Caſtle, during the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing and Healthful Summer, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the benefit of the Air, the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantneſs of their Evening Promenade, the delightful Proſpects of the Meads, Paſtures, Fruitful and Delightful Fields of Corn, and all thoſe inexpreſſible ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions that uſually attend the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renity of a Rural Life, and when wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, or rather refreſhed with theſe Pleaſures, return to their City-Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; either for the Management of
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:109001:66"/> Affairs, or the enjoyment of the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety and Choice of the more Gentile and better ſort of Company. Here they both ſoon obtain by their <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Pence,</hi> Acquaintance of all <hi>Sorts</hi> and <hi>Tempers,</hi> ſo that 'tis impoſſible in ſuch a <hi>World</hi> of <hi>People,</hi> but they muſt neceſſarily meet thoſe that comply with them in temper and humour. To Plays, Revels, Maſquesat Court, they daily reſort, and to other Places, when they receive Information of them; ſo that there is no Publick Treat or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion can poſſibly eſcape, and in ſmall time, gaining great Acquaintance, and that with great Ones too, according as the times, he muſt needs Rencoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as well as his Lady, with no ſmall or trivial <hi>Temptations.</hi> After they have ſteer'd this courſe ſome years, the Real Eſtate ſinks and impairs too too ſenſibly, and which is worſt of all, they both prove Improliſic (and poſſibly the <hi>Curſe of Barrenneſs</hi> is the puniſhment of their Debauchery) ſo that by a ſtrange kind of unuſual, tho mutual conſent, he procures a <hi>Chargeable Miſs,</hi> and ſhe an <hi>Expenſive Gallant,</hi> he ſhakes his <hi>Elbow,</hi> and ſhe her <hi>Tail,</hi> and in proceſs of time, they become equally experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:109001:66"/> in both theſe faſhionable Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations; ſo that in ſome few annual Revolutions, the Eſtate conſumes, and moulders away to nothing, by Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gages and vaſt Debts contracted, the Retinue is turn'd off for want of Means to ſupport them, as formerly, Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeping laid aſide, and the <hi>Moveable Goods</hi> pawn'd or ſold outright, to maintain them. Upon this, being ſear'd and grown obſtinately Profligate and ſenſeleſs of their <hi>Vanity</hi> and <hi>Impiety,</hi> through cuſtomary ſinning, they conſult how to repair their conſumptive and almoſt expired <hi>Fortunes,</hi> by <hi>Injurious, Illegal, Baſe</hi> and <hi>Sordid Actions,</hi> which at length bring them to a ſhameful <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtrophe,</hi> being both too <hi>haughty</hi> and <hi>high Spirited,</hi> to live in a <hi>low</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicable Condition;</hi> therefore he turns <hi>Pad,</hi> and ſhe <hi>Buttock</hi> and <hi>File,</hi> (that is <hi>Highway-Man</hi> and <hi>Pick-Pocket-Whore,</hi> in plain, honeſt <hi>Engliſh,</hi> according to the <hi>Canting</hi> of the <hi>Roguiſh-Crew</hi>) into which they are now admitted and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triculate. Well! what think you fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows theſe wicked Reſolutions, to take up a wicked courſe of Life? why, you may ſoon gueſs, tho <hi>Fortune</hi> ſeem to favour them for ſome time, ſucceſs ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:109001:67"/> ſmiles long upon ſuch <hi>wretched <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakers,</hi> but uſually brings them to <hi>Condign Puniſhment.</hi> Poſſibly, afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſome perpetrated Villanies, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of their as yet ſucceſsful <hi>Crime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> may furniſh them with a <hi>Stock,</hi> in ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of unavoidable neceſſity, when the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are firmly catch'd in the <hi>Net</hi> of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Law</hi> (as formerly they were in that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Matrimony</hi>) This may prevail once o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> twice by a <hi>Lucky</hi> and <hi>Chargeable</hi>—bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this proving no caution, but rather a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> encouragement to repeat their forme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Courſes,</hi> they go on as vigorouſly a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> before, and by skulking in privat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> holes, and obſcure receſſes, ſtave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves off from the ſtrict inquiſition o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Juſtice;</hi> but at length, (for now thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Wicked Reign</hi> is near its period) ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> crafty <hi>Officers,</hi> accuſtomed to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in ſuch Affairs, and by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> means of ſome injur'd perſon, allure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thereunto by the promiſe of a goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gratuity, ſearches diligently, find<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them ſuddenly, and, by the neceſſary of a Juſtices <hi>Mittimus,</hi> conveys the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> immediately, without <hi>Bail</hi> or <hi>Main<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> priſe,</hi> to a Loathſome and Fatal Gao<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> The Seiſions are now at hand, and they in a <hi>Panick Fear,</hi> that they ſhall no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:109001:67"/> come off, being conſcious of their <hi>Guilt:</hi> Well! to a Trial they are brought, and their Indictment contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Crimes for which they are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed: they then have recourſe to <hi>Newgate</hi>-Evaſions, <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Shams (I mean <hi>Lying</hi> and <hi>Diſſembling</hi>) and ſuch kind of inſignificant Triflings with the Court, who, tired out therewith, direct the Jury (who never Read <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus</hi>) and they, upon a full Hearing of the Evidence, bring them in Guilty: Upon this, Sentence of Death is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, and they are ſent to their laſt Habitation here, as faſt tied by the Executioner here, as they by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves formerly. The Warrant being Signed for their Execution, and the day appointed, (there being no hopes of a Pardon, having already deſpiſed and abuſed that Grace and Favour) they are acquainted therewith in order to their Preparation, to undergo the deſerved and unavoidable Puniſhment of the Law, Death. The <hi>Fatal Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> appearing, they are made ready for their laſt Journey, to their long Home, and ſo diſgracefully Carted to <hi>Tyburn;</hi> where by the way, being as notoriouſly known, as they were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:109001:68"/> in the Tranſactions of their Life; ſome (who have <hi>Charity</hi>) pity them, many (who have ſuffered upon their account) <hi>Curſe</hi> them, and moſt blame them. This is a hopeful <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> of the <hi>Tye of Marriage,</hi> which brings them at laſt to be Tyed up by <hi>Ketch,</hi> both indiſſoluble Knots, except untied by the cold hand of Death. Thus you ſee tho the Sun-ſhine of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of their Life ſeem'd to be poſſibly glorious, 'twas at length over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt, and tho they might have liv'd happily, did in the latter part live wretchedly, and died ignominiouſly, ſo they might ſay of themſelves, as the Poet did, with little Alteration—
<q>
                     <l>Per varios caſus, &amp; tot diſcrimina rerum</l>
                     <l>Tendimus in Laqueum—</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus, with them, ends the <hi>Seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Comfort.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="comment">
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:109001:68"/>
               <head>The Eighteenth COMFORT. The Miſery of forc'd Marriage</head>
               <p>NOW (with this which is the laſt, and too many, unleſs they were better) we ſhall run through a petty Jury, and a half, of Pretty and petty <hi>Comforts</hi> too, tho this exceeds all that is premention'd, and may afford ſome <hi>Diverſion,</hi> but far more <hi>Admiration and Aſtoniſhment.</hi> The Story is as followeth, which wants neither Truth, nor Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentic Authors to maintain it. A Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant and Heroic Gentleman, altogether Martial, a Noted Commander, and of a very Ancient Extract; it was his <hi>good Fortune,</hi> as he innocently and probably conjectured, to make his Addreſſes to a <hi>Young Beautiful Gentlewoman,</hi> (but ſee how that <hi>Fickle Baggage Fortune</hi> puts tricks upon Credulous Mortals) and after they had made and received ſeveral Viſits, and ſo united themſelves by the Amorous Chains of Paſſionate and Unfeigned Affection, that they thought nothing but that Cruel Deſtiny <hi>Atropos</hi> could ſeparate them. But it fell out, and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:109001:69"/> very unluckily too) that the Ladies Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, (whoſe Eyes are always prying into ſuch Intrigues) by ſome means and rewards to encourage the Diſcoverers, to prevent their deſign, ſhuffled up a <hi>Match</hi> between their Daughter and a very great Heir, with Menaces, Threats, ſevere Uſage, ſo that weary of their Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage towards her, ſhe was at laſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd, tho with unimaginable regret, and great reluctancy, to embrace the Perſon ſhe had an abſolute indiſpoſition, unfitneſs of mind, and averſion for, ever likely to hinder the many Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of <hi>Conjugal Society,</hi> namely, Peace and Comfort; but it is Decreed by a Law as unalterable as that of the <hi>Mede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> that ſhe muſt undergo thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> inſupportable wearineſs. The Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, who in truth was, or at leaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ought to be her Husband, endeavours to make way for an Interview with her, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> finding all means ineffectual (ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing ſo cloſely mew'd up, (another <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort</hi> of <hi>Forced Marriage</hi>) by her Eagle-ey'd and <hi>Jealous Husband,</hi> inſomuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that nothing could be tranſacted, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he muſt neceſſarily find out, for <hi>Zelo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>typiae nihil impervium,</hi> Jealouſie is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quick-ſighted to be diſappointed by a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:109001:69"/> endeavours whatſoever, whereupon he reſolves to take other meaſures, and therefore in great diſcontent (ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he could not poſſibly procure the ſight of the ſo much admired and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved) he quits his <hi>Native Country</hi> to Travel in queſt of ſome Comfort in Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Parts: We will now leave him in his Journey, and return to ſee how this <hi>new Married Lady</hi> bears her Affliction. She poor <hi>Inamorata,</hi> tho diſappointed of enjoying the <hi>Sole Object</hi> of her <hi>Love,</hi> (what a curſed <hi>Humour</hi> is this of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,</hi> for a cram'd Coffer to confine them to the Land of Affliction?) cannot be debarred the Privilege of thought, and therefore to manage that with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Prudence and Privacy, ſhe affects Retirement, and there bewailes her <hi>Misfortune</hi> in the enjoying this man, as well as in the utter Loſs of her abſent Lover (which prov'd too true at laſt, to her own deſtruction) thinks hourly of the bliſsful and harmleſs <hi>Embraces</hi> of her <hi>Valiant Mars,</hi> the mutual and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Proteſtations that paſſed between them at every aſſignation, the <hi>Poems,</hi> Acroſtics, <hi>Anagrams,</hi> and the whole <hi>Artillery</hi> of <hi>Love,</hi> that they uſed between one
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:109001:70"/> another. This was her <hi>ſole delight,</hi> her da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſure, and all the contentation that ſhe ever enjoy'd in <hi>her Matrimonial</hi> (<hi>tho</hi> unfortunate) <hi>Condition:</hi> and tho all theſe private Solaces were ſhrowded with all Honeſt and Modeſt Contrivances, yet her Carriage to her <hi>Husband</hi> did not ſeem ſo obliging to him, as he thought he might deſerve, and therefore could impute it to nothing but unto the ſudden diſappointment of the Gentleman, who formerly Courted; who would certainly have ſtudied to procure his Deſtruction by ſome means or other, but that he knew he had deſerted the country, and went a way <hi>Incognito,</hi> ſo that there was no great Fear or Probability of his coming to careſs his Lady; but alas! he is miſtaken; for his End is by ſuperiour Power otherwiſe appointed. And now let us return to our Traveller; when he arrived at the place, there happened to be War in thoſe parts, who being <hi>Magnanimous</hi> and <hi>Martial,</hi> (having loſt his Lady, ſcorn'd his Life) he went immediately into the Wars, and was entertain'd according to his <hi>Deſert</hi> and <hi>Quality;</hi> the Enemy being near at hand, he accoutred himſelf for an Attaque, which he did attempt with that <hi>Briskneſs</hi> and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:109001:70"/> 
                  <hi>Valour</hi> (among thoſe in the <hi>Front</hi>) that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but one ſtimulated by <hi>Love,</hi> and a Contempt of his Life and Perſon, could ever have ſo valiantly performed; but behold the unlucky Chance of War! He in this over-Manful Aſſault, received a <hi>Mortal Wound,</hi> to the great grief of thoſe who were ſpectators of his <hi>Valour</hi> and <hi>Courage,</hi> whereupon he was imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately brought off, and convey'd to his own Lodgings; where arrived, he languiſhed ſome little time, and a little before his Death, he called an <hi>Ancient Servant</hi> to him (whoſe <hi>Fidelity and Truth</hi> he had often experienced) and told him, that he had, at this juncture of time, a weighty Buſineſs to unbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to him, and intruſt him with, conjuring him by all imaginable, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging Expreſſions and Deſires to ſee it effected, which was as followeth: I am ſenſible (ſaith he) that I am very near my Expiration, and therefore after my <hi>Death,</hi> procure ſome <hi>Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons</hi> to open my <hi>Body,</hi> take the <hi>Heart</hi> out of my <hi>Breaſt,</hi> and put it into an <hi>Earthen-Pot,</hi> that it may be <hi>Baked</hi> to the conſiſtence of a <hi>Fine Powder,</hi> and having ſo done, put it into a handſome <hi>Box</hi> with this <hi>Bracelet of Hair,</hi> that he
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:109001:71"/> had worn about his <hi>Left Wriſt</hi> (being a <hi>Lock</hi> of his <hi>Lady</hi> before mentioned) then place it in the <hi>Powder,</hi> together with this little <hi>Billet or Note,</hi> written with my own <hi>Blood</hi> to her, and after you have beſtowed upon me the <hi>Rites</hi> of a <hi>Decent</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian Burial,</hi> make all poſſible ſpeed to her in her own <hi>Country,</hi> (which you know very well as well as her place of Reſidence) and deliver the ſaid <hi>Box</hi> to her own hands. The <hi>Old, True Servant,</hi> did perform all that his <hi>Maſter</hi> had given him i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Command, and ſo departed; arriving with great <hi>Expedition,</hi> at the <hi>Country</hi> and <hi>Place</hi> deſigned by his <hi>Maſter;</hi> and coming one day to her <hi>Houſe,</hi> he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luckily, tho unexpectedly was ſurpriſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by the <hi>Ladies Husband,</hi> who knew hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> very well, and that he was <hi>Servan</hi> to that <hi>Gentleman</hi> who formerly mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Applications</hi> to his <hi>Lady;</hi> and he exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined him with a <hi>Brow-beating</hi> ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and finding him timorous, and he ſitating in his Diſcourſe and Repli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> made no more ado but ranſackt hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and found the forementioned <hi>Box</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his <hi>Pocket,</hi> with the <hi>Note,</hi> which ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified what was contained in it; h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Husband</hi> upon this diſmiſt the <hi>Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="125" facs="tcp:109001:71"/> Servant</hi> with Menaces, charging him never more to approach his Houſe upon his own peril, and ſo the poor Servant departed <hi>reinfecta,</hi> and his Maſter's Commands uneffected, tho' by Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune (as he thought certainly) diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey'd. The Gentleman thereupon ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reenters his Houſe, ſends for his Cook, and delivers him the Pouder, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al charging him to make ſome ſmall ſavoury Diſh of it, without loſing the leaſt particle of it, upon the forfeiture of his abſolute diſpleaſure, becauſe it was a very coſtly <hi>Cordial,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to bring it in himſelf after the laſt Courſe at Supper; and the Cook did ſo accordingly: as ſoon as it was placed on the Table, he orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all Perſons to quit the Room, which was no ſooner ſaid than done; and ſo began to enter into a moſt ſerious Diſcourſe with his Wife; how that ever ſince his <hi>Marriage,</hi> he obſerved her <hi>Dejected, Melancholick Carriage,</hi> and he did very much fear, that it was oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd by ſome inward <hi>Conſumption,</hi> therefore he had made proviſion of a very Sovereign Remedy, which he was very well ſatisfied would cure her infallibly; thereupon he made her eat
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:109001:72"/> it all up, and when ſhe had ſo done in obedience to him, very earneſtly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portun'd him to diſcover what it was, who told her for ſatisfaction at laſt, that ſhe had eaten her firſt Courtiers Heart, ſo drew the Box out of his Poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, and ſhew'd her the Note and Bracelet, at which in a ſuddain Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſportation, uſher'd with a deep ſigh, ſaid, <hi>This is Precious indeed,</hi> and lickt the Diſh clean, ſaying, <hi>it is ſo Precious, that 'tis pity any other Meat ſhould be taken down after it;</hi> thus ſhe went to Bed, and made good her words; for in the Morning ſhe was found Stone-dead.</p>
               <p>Now I preſume you are ſatisfied with the ſtrangeneſs of this unparallel'd Comfort, the mere effect of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſive Marriage againſt Reaſon, Senſe and nature, to the Ruine of their own Daughter, and the Death of a Worthy and Valiant Gentleman, tho both to be commended as much for their Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Conſtancy, as the Parent were to be blamed for their Violence and Covetouſneſs, tho ſhe had at laſt the two Hearts joyned together, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of Father and Fate, yet upon my Heart I cannot away with this kind o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cannibal-like and Unnatural Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:109001:72"/>
               <p>Thus we have done with theſe Eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Comforts of Matrimony; and I call them Comforts, becauſe thoſe that are Married think them ſo, and will not be perſwaded to the contrary, tho I look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them as the worſt of Misfortunes. I do not, nay I dare not ſay, that every Married Man taſtes of all theſe <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts;</hi> But I will affirm this for truth, that there is no wedded Perſon living, how Wiſe and Cautelous ſoever, but is ſenſible, at the leaſt, of one of theſe <hi>Comforts.</hi> Nor on the other hand do I ſay it is ill done to Marry; but it is not well done certainly, for a man to be ſo Stupid and Inſenſible, as thoſe we here Diſcourſe of apparently declare themſelves to be, and ſo are enſlaved with a ſelf-procured Bondage. I would not willingly diſoblige the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Sex, nor indeed do I, if read without Prejudice, and rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, the <hi>Contents</hi> of this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding much to their Honour and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, in all which Rencounters the Women win the day, come off Triumphantly, and Man is moſt ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully worſted by the weaker Sex: and 'tis but reaſon it ſhould be ſo, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:109001:73"/> the Wrongs that they ſuffer by the Oppreſſion and Severity of their Husbands, by <hi>Violence,</hi> and without Reaſon; only becauſe they are not of ſo Robuſtous Conſtitution, and are ſent into the World with no other Weapon but the Tongue, nor any other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence but their Chaſtity, tho daily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the <hi>crafty Aſſaults</hi> of <hi>Wily Man:</hi> Nature having ſent them ſo weakly Arm'd into the World, it is a prodigious ſhame, that Men ſhould ſo barbarouſly inſult over them, who are ſo ready to ſerve and obey, without whoſe Society the <hi>World</hi> would ſoon be a <hi>Deſart,</hi> nay Men could not, did not, nor cannot live happily.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:109001:73"/>
            <head>Some Books lately Printed for <hi>Matthew Gillyflower,</hi> at the Black Spread Eagle-in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>THe <hi>Compleat Gard'ner,</hi> or Directions for Cultivating and right ordering of <hi>Fruit-Gardens,</hi> and <hi>Kitchen-Gardens,</hi> in ſix Books, by the Famous Monſieur <hi>De la Quintinye.</hi> To which is added, his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of <hi>Orange-Trees,</hi> with the raiſing of <hi>Melons,</hi> omitted in the <hi>French</hi> Edition, made <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>John Evelyn,</hi> Eſq;</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cabala,</hi> Myſteries of State and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in Letters of Illuſtrious Perſons and Great Miniſters of State, as well Foreign as Domeſtick, in the Reign of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> K. <hi>James,</hi> and K. <hi>Charles.</hi> To which is added in this Third Edition, a Second Part of Choice Original Letters and Negotiations, never before Publiſhed.</item>
               <item>Fables of <hi>Aeſop</hi> and other Eminent My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thologiſts, with Morals and Reflections, by Sir <hi>Roger L'Eſtrange.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Brownlow Latini Redivivus,</hi> a Book of Entries, of ſuch Declarations, Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Pleas in Bar, and Abatement, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> contained in the Firſt and Second parts of the Declarations and Pleadings of <hi>Richard Brownlow,</hi> late Chief Prothonotary of the <hi>Common Pleas,</hi> (unskilfully turn'd into <hi>Engliſh</hi>) now Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed
<pb facs="tcp:109001:74"/> in their Original Latin, with Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of Authentick Modern Preſidents, under every Title.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Eſſays of Seigneur de Montaigne,</hi> in three Books, with a ſhort Character of the Author and Tranſlator, by way of Letter, written by the Marqueſs <hi>Halyfax,</hi> made <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>Charles Cotton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi>'s <hi>Morals,</hi> Tranſlated from the <hi>Greek,</hi> by ſeveral Hands, in 5 Volumes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Kalendarium Hortenſe,</hi> or the Gard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner's Almanack, directing what he is to do <hi>Monthly</hi> throughout the Year, and what <hi>Fruits</hi> and <hi>Flowers</hi> are in prime. To which is added, a new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatory or Green-houſe, with many other uſeful Additions, by <hi>John Evelyn,</hi> Eſq;</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Memorials</hi> of the Method and Manner of Proceedings in Parliament, in paſſing Bills; with the Rules, Cuſtoms, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Houſe, gathered out of the Journal Books, from the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th, by <hi>Hen. Scobel,</hi> Eſq; Cler. Parl.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Remembrances</hi> of Methods, Orders and Proceedings in the Houſe of Lords, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted out of the Journals of that Houſe, by <hi>Hen. Scobel,</hi> Eſq; Cler. Parl. To which is added, the Priviledge of the Barronage of <hi>England,</hi> both in and out of Parliament, Collected by <hi>John Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> Eſq;</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:109001:74"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
